<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="148"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[MESSAGE FROM THE PRINCIPAL









                                                      Forensic Science is playing an important

                                                      role in the criminal justice system and its

                                                      impact is getting stronger each passing
                                                      year. The applied field of science which
                                                      caters to free and fair justice in the world

                                                      is dynamic and has the scope to advance

                                                      with every new advancement in the vast
                                                      field of science. The improvements in the

                                                      field of crime scene reconstruction, DNA
                                                      evidence analysis, cyber crime invest-

       igation and multimedia forensics are driving the field into newer arenas

       which were not ventured before. At this juncture, information on forensic
       topics are multi-various and hosted on multiple platforms, making it dif-

       ficult for an information-seeker to access it.
       The Department of Forensic Science at Kristu Jayanti College (Autono-

       mous), Bengaluru runs a Bachelor’s and Master’s in Science in Forensic
       Science programmes. The department has been in the forefront to provide

       holistic and experiential growth to the students training in the department
       and has regularly organized invited talks, seminars and workshops to ex-

       pose them to the first-hand recent information in the various disciplines

       of Forensic Science.
       The Forensic Science newsletter, ‘Veritas’ is a bi-annual newsletter which

       compiles articles written by the forensic science students on matters relat-
       ing to research areas,  case studies, newer  technologies  etc. The previous

       issues of Veritas has set a covetable standard with respect to content, de-
       sign and quality. The editorial board of the newsletter comprised of teach-

       ers and students have worked hard to provide a rich and effective reading

       experience to the readers.
       On this occasion, I congratulate the department of Forensic Science and

       the  editorial  board  of Veritas  for  the  successful  and  effective  issue  of  the
       third edition.


                                                                 Rev. Fr. Augustine George,

                                                                              Principal

                                                 1]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[MESSAGE FROM THE DEAN










                                                              The ecosystem of the Department

                                                              of Forensic Science provides suf-
                                                              ficient and compelling setting for

                                                              our students to learn, work togeth-
                                                              er and to involve in curricular and

                                                              co-curricular activities.  These ac-
                                                              tivities help the students to imag-

                                                              ine, innovate and build the future
                                                              in  this  exciting  field.  I  am  happy

                                                              that  The Department of Forensic
                                                              Science at Kristu Jayanti College,

       Autonomous, is coming out with the 3rd edition of Veritas, the bi-annual

       Forensic Science newsletter. The present issue of Veritas is brought out
       with the intent to enlighten the reader on pertinent information related

       to the field, to highlight the activities of the Department and therefore
       the dynamism of its community. The appealing design and ease of access

       has been the strength of  Veritas. Congratulations to the students and
       faculty members who have contributed to the content and tothe editorial

       team comprising of faculty members and students who have taken ex-

       treme care in reviewing the articles, designing the templates and creating
       this brilliant issue of the newsletter.

       Wishing each of you the best!
























                                                                     Dr. Calistus Jude A. L.,

                                                                  Dean, Faculty of Sciences

                                                  2]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[-























                                             CONTENTS
















               •  Commemorating 75 years of Indian Indepen-


                   dence

               •  Department of Forensic Science- Activities

               •  Research articles

               •  Global news updates related to forensic science

               •  Case studies

               •  Feature articles

               •  Literature review


               •  Statistical data





























                                                             5]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[-
       COMMEMORATING 75 YEARS OF



       INDIAN INDEPENDENCE




       On the midnight of 15th August

       1947, India marked an end to the
       200-year-long struggle for Indian

       independence and  put  a perma-

       nent end to the British rule.  The

          struggle was never easy. It took

       the blood and effort of millions of

       Indians.  The movement towards becoming a free and indepen-

       dent  nation  was  spearheaded  by  leaders  like  B.G  Tilak, C.S Azad,
       Bhagat Singh, G.K. Gokhale, Mahatma Gandhi and manyothers.




       The movement and the independence, however, was a result of

       the efforts of the leaders, the snowballing effort of several unsung

       heroes and the common citizens of the country have played an

       important role in it. India’s grapple never fails to instill a sense of

       pride in its citizens.  The Indian independence day of 2022 is re-
       markable. To celebrate and commemorate 75 year of Indian inde-

       pendence, Hon’ble Prime Minister Shri. Narendra Modi initiated a

       celebration -Azadi Ka Amrit Mahotsav (AKAM). The  celebration

       commenced on  12th March 2021, with a 75-week countdown to

       15th August 2022 to mark 75 years of Indian independence. The

       five themes of AKAM were -
       •  Freedom struggle: It aims to acknowledge and honour the valor

          of thousands of freedom fighters and unsung heroes in help-

          ing India achieve Independence. Few events observed under the

          theme include Birsa Munda Jayanti (Janjatiya Gaurav Diwas),

          Declaration  of Provisional  Government  of Free India by Netaji,

          and Shaheed Diwas.
       •  Ideas@75: The theme Ideas@75 brings into the limelight the ac-

          tivities and gatherings driven by various notions and philoso-



                                                           6]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[phies that helped shape India and that will continue to do so in
         the next 25 years. The period from India’s 75th to 100th

         independence year called the AmritKaal. The theme encompas-

         es events like Kashi Utsav, a cultural and heritage festival to cel-

         ebrate the legacy of Kashi, and Post Cards to the Prime Minister,

         where students from grades 4-12 pen their letters to the Hon’ble

         Prime Minister on themes like “The Unsung Heroes of Freedom
         Struggle” and “My Vision for India in 2047”.

      •  Resolve@75:  The  theme  is  focused  on  achieving  the  goals  and

         targets of the nation through good plans, collective efforts, and

         a vision for the motherland. Programs like Constitution Day and

         Good Governance Week fall under the theme.

      •  Actions@75: The theme centers around the efforts the Indian gov-
         ernment is taking to help India rise on a global scale. It looks for-

         ward to the collective effort of all the people and organizations in

         the country to rise to its global competitors. It looks into different

         government policies and action plans to make the nation a better

         place for its citizens. Few initiatives under the theme include Gati

         Shakti - National Master Plan for Multi-Modal Connectivity and

         WEP Nxt: An Initiative to Nurture Women Entrepreneurship.
      •  Achievements@75:  The theme Achievements@75 takes a look at

         the landmark achievements that the nation has witnessed up to the

         75th year of independence. Swarnim Vijay Varsh and the opening

         of the ShreshthaYojana during MahaparinirvanDiwas are a few

         events recognized under the theme.




      Another initiative that was part of Azadi Ka Amrit Mahotsav was
      “Har  Ghar Tiranga”.  The initiative encouraged all Indian citizens

      to unfurl the tricolor Indian flag in their homes or workplaces. The

      HarGharTirangacampaign began on 13th August 2022 and contin-

      ued to 15th August 2022.More than 5 crore tricolor flags have been

      pinned on the Indian land showing the unity and pride of Indians in

      their nation.





                                                             7]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[Aatmanirbhar Bharat was another initiative the Prime Minister put

       forth during AKAM.  The notion of a self-reliant nation is what is
       being envisioned and is similar to the “Make In India” movement.

       It aims to encourage Indian nationals to stay in the nation and

       serve its finance and economy in many different ways possible.

       Through such initiatives, India seeks to achieve Independence 2.0,

       a path to meeting sustainable development goals and becoming the

       so-aspired  “Nation of  the future”.  The  Prime Minister  has indeed

       put forth a strong message for all Indians, taking inspiration from
       the long-drawn freedom struggle. It is one such moment in history

       that will never cease to inspire the youth to serve the nation.




       From the Editors:

       This issue of  Veritas, the forensic science newsletter published

       bi-annually by the Department of Forensic Science at Kristu Jayanti

       College, Autonomous, Bangalore, is a special edition commemo-
       rating the 75 years of Indian independence. Kristu Jayanti College,

       Bangalore, had organized several events across all the different de-

       partments to cherish the historic day and foster patriotism in the

       present youth. The Department of Economics organized a celebra-

       tion themed “Heroes of India’s Freedom - Revisiting History” that

       included pledges, elocution, quiz, and polls, and the Department

       of English organized  “The Song of Freedom” (singing competi-
       tion) and “The Freedom Quiz” (quiz competition).

       The Department of Forensic Science organized a poster-making

       competition for all the UG students. The participants were asked to

       create posters using only finger and palm prints (a unique element

       of Forensic Science) with the theme being Indian independence,

       freedom struggle, and patriotism. The highlights of the event have

       been published in the following section.



       References:

       •  Themes of “Azadi Ka Amrit Mahotsav” (Celebrating 75 years of

          Indian Independence). (n.d.). Retrieved August 23, 2022, from



                                                             8]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[https://cgimelbourne.gov.in/public_files/assets/pdf/flyer.pdf

       •  HarGharTiranga. (n.d.). Harghartiranga.com. Retrieved August
          23, 2022, from https://harghartiranga.com/digital-tiranga

       •  Bureau, A. N. (2022, August 5). Azadi Ka Amrit Mahotsav: 5

          Themes  To Commemorate India’s 75  Years Of Independence.

          News.abplive.com.                     https://news.abplive.com/news/india/aza-

          di-ka-amrit-mahotsav-5-themes-to-commemorate-india-s-75-

          years-of-independence-1546251

       •  Independence Day Essay. (n.d.).  VEDANTU. https://www.ve-
          dantu.com/english/independence-day-essay

       •  Essay on India’s Struggle For Independence. (2014, July 31). His-

          tory  Discussion  - Discuss  Anything  about History. https://www.

          historydiscussion.net/essay/essay-on-indias-struggle-for-inde-

          pendence/2099






















































                                         Poster by- A. Sherlin Gomez

                                                  (III Sem BSc. FS)

                                                           9]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[Poster by- Swetha Ann Mathew
                                                  (V Sem BSc. FS)









































                                             Poster by- Varun Sai S.

                                                  (I Sem BSc. FS)

                                                             10]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Brief Write-up on the Programme:





      In tune with  ‘AzadikaAmritMahotsav’ a GoI initiative, the Depart-

      ment  of  Forensic  Science  at  Kristu  Jayanti  College,  Autonomous
      organized a poster competition for the students belonging to the

      department.  The call for posters was circulated on 12th August

      2022.  The rules of the contest were to create a poster on chart

      paper using fingerprints and palm prints, to have relevance to Fo-

      rensic Science. The theme of the competition was the Indian Inde-

      pendence movement, freedom struggle and the progress India has

      made in the 75 years of independence.
      Students from the department of Forensic Science participated in

      the event enthusiastically with fervor and submitted their creations.

      The posters were displayed in the Forensic Science Laboratory 2,

      third floor, main block on 19th August 2022.  The Principal, Kristu

      Jayanti College, Rev. Dr. Augustine George graced the event with

      his presence.  The dean, Faculty of Science, Dr. Calistus Jude A L

      and the faculty members of the department along with the partici-
      pant students highlighted the meaning of the posters, the learning

      points from the activity and the impact it had on their sense of pa-

      triotism. Students and faculty members of Kristu Jayanti College

      visited the venue and witnessed the posters created by the students.

      The posters were judged and the best three posters were awarded.



      Posters displayed in the venue



























                                                             11]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[Principal Rev. Fr. Augustine George interacting with the participants






         List of winners:





                    Position                   Register number                     Student name




                       First                         21FRSB01                    A Sherlin Gomez





                     Second                        20LS3H1050                        Swetha Ann
                                                                                        Mathew


                       Third                         22FRSB60                         Varun Sai S





























                                                             12]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[-


















                                    DEPARTMENT OF



                                FORENSIC SCIENCE-



                                             ACTIVITIES










       •  International conference on advances in forensic science

          (icafs) 2022

       •  Inquisitor - inter-collegiate forensic science fest

       •  Career orientation session on cyber forensics and cyber

          security

       •  Atrium - intra-collegiate forensic science fest


       •  Guest lecture on practical approaches to questioned docu-

          ment examination

       •  In-house career orientation session

       •  Guest lecture on the role of forensic medicine in crime in-

          vestigation

       •  Guest lecture on disaster victim identification






















                                                             13]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[-
                    INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE


                                     ON ADVANCES IN




                  FORENSIC SCIENCE (ICAFS) 2022






         On 5th and 6th May 2022, the Department of Forensic Science,

         Kristu Jayanti College hosted the first edition of  “Internation-

         al Conference on Advances in Forensic Science (ICAFS)”.  With

         more  than 300  participants, the conference  was aimed at  pro-

         viding a platform for researchers, academicians, learners, and
         industry professionals to discuss, deliberate, and grow in the

         field of Forensic Science.

                                                  Inauguration

         Dr. Calistus Jude A L, Dean, Faculty of Science, Kristu Jayanti

         College, welcomed the chief guest, resource persons, and the

         delegates to the conference. Sir stressed on the need for constant

         upskilling in this technology-oriented field of Forensic Science.
         Dr. Shayani Ghosh, Assistant Professor, Department of Foren-

         sic Science and Convener of ICAFS 2022, gave a prelude to the

         conference and entailed that the conference would have 4 tech-

         nical sessions with a wide range of topics spanning the different

         domains of Forensic Science and also have multiple oral and

         poster presentations from the registered delegates.



         The  conference  was  inaugurated  by  Mr.  Barry  A  Fisher,  Retired

         Crime Lab Director, Los Angeles County, USA, who is a re-

         nowned author and pioneer in the field of Forensic Science with

         more than 30  years of  field  experience.  The  resource  persons

         included experts from the different major disciplines of Forensic

         science with a range of interesting topics.

         The presidential address during the inauguration was delivered
         by Fr. Lijo P  Thomas, Financial Administrator, Kristu Jayantti

         College who was delighted to have the chief guest and resource



                                                             14]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[persons and delegates for the conference. He quoted the recent

         advancements in the field and requested the delegates to make

         use of this platform and come up with valuable insights in the

         field and also requested the conveners to come up with ways in

         which the conference can be expanded to future years as well.

         The conference was officially inaugurated by Mr. Barry A Fish-
         er, Retired Crime Lab Director, Los Angeles County, USA, who

         addressed the delegates and welcomed them. The theme of sir’s

         talk  was  on  the  recent  advancements  and  future  scopes  in  the

         field. Mr. Fisher cited many new facets, which are the talk of the

         future in the field and set the tone for the conference to ponder

         on the new unknown. He also spoke of areas that may require
         a lot of understanding and may promise to be challenging in the

         recent future and encouraged the delegates to use the two days

         valuably.

         The  session  was  ended  with  a  formal  vote  of  thanks  by  Prof.

         Don Caeiro, Coordinator of the Forensic Science programme at

         Kristu Jayanti College and co-convener of the conference.



         Technical Session 1: Advancements in Forensic Biology: the past,

                                             present, and future.

         The first technical session was addressed by Dr. Arun Sharma,

         Retd. Director, Directorate of Forensics Services, Himachal

         Pradesh, India. Sir, with his vast experience, could detail the

         sequence of improvement in the field of Forensic Biology from
         the past, beginning from the traditional means of investigating

         crimes using biological evidences. He quickly recapped the slow

         beginnings and went on to detail the present setup of the field.

         He  explained  multiple  case  studies,  which  were  points  of  inter-

         est in the Indian context. Sir could also explain using some of

         his experiences on how biological evidences can be very helpful

         but also must be handled with care. Sir could also throw light
         on the future scope of the field, the expected challenges, and




                                                             15]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[how we could face them.

         Finally, the session was concluded by Dr. Sharma answering a

         couple of queries from the delegates about the topic. This session

         proved to be fruitful in enhancing the delegates in the domain
         and could also throw light on the expected growths in the field.




         Technical Session 2: Advances in Anti-doping analysis from her

                           experience in the field of Sports Forensics.

         The second technical session was handled by Dr. Shobha Ahi,

         Deputy Director, Drug Control Centre, King’s College, London,

         UK, who has a vast experience in both India as well as world-
         wide in the field of Anti-doping in sports. Ma’am, with her ex-

         perience, could explain the basics, the protocols, and the report-

         ing mechanism in the field. The delegates were also meticulously

         explained the analysis behind cases involving the use of perfor-

         mance-enhancing drugs in sports.

         Beginning from the collection of samples, ma’am explained the

         extraction techniques, the spot tests, the instrumental techniques
         available, and the interpretation involved in these cases. The use

         of  spectrophotometry  and  chromatography was  explained  in

         great detail. The recent advances were highlighted, and the del-

         egates could understand how the scope of the field is fast evolv-

         ing and the relevance to forensic science and existing forensic

         standards in this field.

         The session ended with questions from the delegates, which were
         patiently and detailedly explained by the speaker.




         Technical Session 3: Emerging challenges in Questioned Docu-

                                              ment Examination

         The third technical session was from the physical science domain
         and focused on the field of Questioned Document Analysis. The

         session was addressed by Dr. J K Semwal, Retd. Senior Faculty

         from the prestigious LNJN NICFS, New Delhi, India, who is an




                                                             16]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[established academician from the prestigious institution. Sir
         started off by explaining about the problems encountered in this

         field due to its subjective nature of examination and reporting.

         He stressed that even though this lacuna exists, it also provides

         for further enhancing the field by the use of careful and validat-

         ed techniques.

         Sir systematically handled each lacuna and broadened the dele-

         gates’ thinking by pointing out the scopes available and listing
         the possible research areas which are emerging in the field. He

         explained about the use of information technology, computer

         systems, artificial intelligence, and statistical modelling and also

         included the possibility of simulated handwriting and signatures.

         The session was highly appreciated by the delegates and offered

         many of them eye-opening ideas.

         The session had a round of questions that were answered by the
         resource person.




         Technical Session 4: Advances in the Digital and Cyber Forensic

                                                      domain.

         The fourth and final technical session was addressed by Dr.

         Meenakshi Mahajan, Deputy Director, Directorate of Forensics

         Services, Himachal Pradesh, India, who has a good track record
         of handling many interesting cases involving digital evidence in

         India. Ma’am, with her vast experience, started with her un-

         derstanding and views of the use of digital evidences and could

         stress on the necessity to think of future challenges in this field.

         She also backed her argument using cases that had been handled
         by her.

         The session had a rich mix of case studies, theories, legal pro-

         visions, and possible emerging challenges in the field. Ma’am

         could also demonstrate the need for relying on digital evidences

         by using the internet to share a glimpse of the impact and fre-

         quency of these crimes She encouraged delegates who were



                                                             17]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[interested in the field to be aware of today’s challenges and be
         prepared for tomorrow’s problems.

         The session had multiple questions being asked by the delegates,

         which were patiently answered by the resource person.




                                     Oral and poster presentations

         There were presentations by delegates pertaining to the fields of

         Forensic Biology, Forensic Chemistry and  Toxicology, Forensic
         Chemical and Biological Sciences, Forensic Physical Sciences,

         and Digital Forensics. A total of 4 oral paper presentation ses-

         sions with 23 individual presentations were held. Each of them

         had interesting insights and new ideas, which sparked interest in

         delegates. The panelists reviewed and provided valuable insights

         to the researchers to further the field of interest.

         Poster  presentations  happened  in  two  different  sessions  with  a
         total of 21 presentations. The posters were creatively designed,

         and very profound facts and findings were shared during these

         sessions.  The panelists were highly appreciative of the posters

         and the quality of the findings.




                                           Valediction ceremony

         The valedictory ceremony happened at the end of the confer-
         ence on the evening of 6th May 2022. Dr. Meenakshi Mahajan,

         Deputy Director, Directorate of Forensics Services, Himachal

         Pradesh, India, was the chief guest for the session and credited

         the delegates for their presence and attention during the confer-

         ence. She praised and motivated the presenters for their research
         and encouraged them to get better in the field. She had words of

         motivation for students who attended the conference and wel-

         comed them for more such sessions.

         Dr. Calistus Jude A L, Dean, Faculty of Science, Kristu Jayanti

         College, thanked the resource persons and panelists for their

         time and expertise they shared during the conference.



                                                             18]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[Prof. Don Caeiro, Coordinator of the Forensic Science pro-

         gramme and co-convener of the conference, read out the prize

         winners  for  the  oral  and  paper  presentations.  Each  oral  session

         had two winners, and poster presentations were valued as a

         whole. The winners and presenters were congratulated for their
         works.

         Dr. Shayani Ghosh, Assistant professor and convener of the con-
                                           INQUISITOR -
         ference, proposed the vote of thanks.



                      INTER - C OLLE GIA TE





































































                                                            19]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[INQUISITOR - INTER-COLLEGIATE



                            FORENSIC SCIENCE FEST







         The  Forensic  Science  Club,  Department  of  Forensic  Science,  or-

         ganized Inquisitor 2022, the first inter-collegiate forensic fest for
         the undergraduate students of forensic science in other colleges

         based  in India. This  forensic fest  aimed  at  discovering students’

         knowledge and understanding of the subject as it offered a wide

         array of science-related events.

         The event was organized by the student coordinators of the Fo-

         rensic Science Club at Kristu Jayanti College, Bangalore.  The

         B.Sc. Forensic Science students at Kristu Jayanti College formed
         the working group and were the event and team organisers. The

         participants included the Forensic Science students from 5 dif-

         ferent institutes across India.




         The fest was executed with a total of 8 events and was organized
    7    at the best of quality. The fest was conducted online due to the


         pandemic situation using the Zoom platform. The high- spirited
         forensic fest started with preliminary rounds of various events

         on 4th April 2021.

         The participants were given participant codes to ensure fairness;

         none  of  the  internal  students  participated,  and  the  event  was

         open only for external participants.
         8 events were organized which included - Crime  Travel (Case

         study),  Crimetoonist  (Sketching),  Hidden  in  Plain  Sight  (Obser-

         vation test), Canvas (Poster),  Trial by  Trivia (Forensic Quiz),

         Tug of  Words (Debate),  Think Detective (Puzzle solving), and

         Sherlock Holmes (Personality contest).




         The inaugural ceremony of the fest was presided over by Fr.
         Joshy Mathew, member of Management, Director library, and




                                                             20]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[coordinator of Dept of English at Kristu Jayanti College, Ban-

         galore, and the guest of honour was Dr. Rakesh Gupta, Joint

         Director,  Forensic Science laboratory, Chhattisgarh. In his  pres-

         idential address, Father enlightened about the importance of Fo-

         rensic Science and its scope in everyday life. Dr. Rakesh Gupta

         spoke about the existing avenues in Forensic Science and the fu-
         ture scopes. He encouraged students to take up newer domains

         and fields which are coming up in the field. He exhorted the

         faculty members to take up newer topics and help the students

         evolve into newer and brighter minds.




         In the valedictory ceremony, Dr. Calistus Jude, Dean, Faculty of

         Science, Kristu Jayanti College, felicitated the winners of various
         events and appreciated the Forensic Science Club coordinators

         for having conducted the forensic fest successfully.

         A total of 81 participants actively participated in the fest from

         the following 5 different institutes.

         1. Government Institute of Forensic Science, Nagpur

         2. School of Social Work (Autonomous)

         3. SGT University
         4. SMS College of Arts and Science

         5. Garden City University, Bangalore

         The participants from the Government Institute of Forensic Sci-

         ence, Nagpur, were declared the overall winners of the fest. Par-

         ticipants of the other institutes too won a good share of prizes

         during the fest.

         The feedback for the fest was overwhelmingly positive, and stu-
         dents could upskill themselves through the different events that

         were organized.















                                                             21]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[CAREER ORIENTATION SESSION



               ON CYBER FORENSICS AND CYBER



                                                SECURITY








         A guest lecture on the topic “Careers in Forensic Science (Cyber

         Forensics and Cyber Security)” was conducted on 5th February

         2022, at 9 AM by the Department of Forensic Science, Kris-

         tu Jayanti College. Mr. Kishalay Masanta, Cyber Security Con-

         sultant Quantum Security Services  Wellington, New Zealand,

         was the resource person for the session. It was conducted over

         the Zoom platform and had over 240 participants. The session
         started off by seeking the blessings of God. Dr. Shayani Ghosh,

         Assistant Professor, Unit of Forensic Science, welcomed the re-

         source person, faculty members, and the students. Mr. Arvind

         T., Professor, Unit of Forensic Science, introduced the resource

         person who had completed his Bachelor’s degree in Jain Uni-

         versity, Bangalore, in B.Sc Forensic Science and Masters degree

         in Information Security and Digital Forensics in the Auckland
         University of  Technology, New Zealand.  The session was then

         taken over by the resource person, who talked about the follow-

         ing to the audience:

         •  What is Cyber Security and Digital Forensics?

         •  The importance of Cyber Security and Forensics

         •  Why should  you  have a  career  in  Cyber Security and  Foren-

             sics?
         •  Some of the Best Universities offering a master’s degree in Cy-

             ber Security and similar fields

         •  Career paths in Cyber Security and Digital Forensics

         •  The  skills  required to  be  chosen  by different  companies  and

             the technical skills needed for being a professional in Cyber

             Security and Digital Forensics field



                                                             22]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[•  The free resources provided by different institutions to in-

            crease your knowledge in different areas of Cyber Security

            and Forensics

        •  Qualifications and certifications to prove your skills

        •  Lastly, the journey of the resource person in the field of Cyber
            Security

        After the session, it was time for the participants to raise their

        queries. The discussion was very interactive, and a lot of partic-

        ipants came forward with their doubts. The vote of thanks was

        given by Ms. Geethu Suresh, Professor, Unit of Forensic Science.
        The ending comments  were shared by Mr. Don  Caeiro, Assis-

        tant Professor, Unit of Forensic Science. The session was highly

        informative, and the participants got to know more about Cy-

        ber Security and Cyber Forensics.
























































                                                            23]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[ATRIUM - INTRA-COLLEGIATE



                            FORENSIC SCIENCE FEST









         The Forensic Science Club, Unit of Forensic Science, organized

         Atrium 2022, an intra-collegiate forensic fest for the first and

         second-year undergraduate students of Forensic Science.  This
         forensic fest aimed at discovering students’ knowledge and un-

         derstanding of the subject as it offered a wide range of science-re-

         lated events.




         The event was organized by the student coordinators of the Fo-

         rensic Science Club at Kristu Jayanti College, Bangalore. The fi-

         nal year students formed the working group and were the event
         and team organisers. The participants included the first and sec-

         ond-year Forensic Science students.

         Some of the events included were Crucipher (Crossword), Crime

         Travel (Case study presentation), Internal Affairs (Just A Min-

         ute), and  Think Detective (Online  Treasure hunt).  The event
         named Sherlock Holmes took the participants through a series

         of investigative rounds.




         The fest was executed with a total of 15 events and was organized

         at its best of quality. The fest was conducted online due to the

         pandemic situation using the Zoom platform. The high-spirited

         forensic fest started with preliminary rounds of various events
         on 7th February 2021.

         12 teams formed by the students participated in good spirit,

         and the preliminary rounds and final rounds had very interest-

         ing  themes  and  games. Team  names  included  Sokovia,  Lamen-

         tis,  Vormir,  Asgard,  Wakanda,  Ragnarok, Midgard,  Kree,  Titan,

         Sanctum, Xandar, and Quantum.




                                                             24]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[15 events were organized which included - Crucipher (Cross-

         word), Crime  Travel (Case study), Aftermath (Documentary),

         Crimetoonist (Sketching), Hidden in Plain Sight (Observation

         test), Canvas (Poster), Hostage (Roleplay),  Total Recall (Report

         writing), Internal Affairs (Just a Minute), Oh Snap (Photogra-
         phy), Once Upon a Crime (Crime fiction writing), Trial by Trivia

         (Forensic  Quiz),  Tug of  Words  (Debate),  Think  Detective  (Puz-

         zle solving), and Sherlock Holmes (Personality contest).




         The inaugural ceremony of the fest was presided over by Fr.
         Augustine  George, Principal, Kristu Jayanti College, and the

         guest of honour was Ms. Maalini Ramalo, Director for Social

         Protection, Development of Human Resources for Rural Areas

         (DHRRA), Malaysia. In his presidential address, Father enlight-

         ened about the importance of Forensic Science and its scope in

         everyday life. Ms. Maalini spoke about her role in the domain

         of social protection and how the knowledge of forensic science
         helps her carry out day-to-today roles. She encouraged students

         to keep upskilling and following their dreams and motivated

         them to use opportunities provided during such fests to empow-

         er themselves.

         In the valedictory ceremony, Dr. Calistus Jude, Dean, Faculty of

         Science, Kristu Jayanti College, felicitated the winners of various

         events and appreciated the Forensic Science Club coordinators
         for having conducted the forensic fest successfully.


























                                                            25]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[GUEST LECTURE ON PRACTICAL



                   APPROACHES TO QUESTIONED



                        DOCUMENT EXAMINATION








         A guest lecture on the topic  “Practical Approaches to Ques-

         tioned Document Examination” was conducted on 19th Feb-

         ruary 2022 at 9:30 AM by the Department of Forensic Science,

         Kristu Jayanti College. Mr. Sharwan Kumar, Case reporting of-

         ficer, Central Forensic Science Laboratory, Chandigarh, was the

         resource person for the session.  The program was conducted

         over the Zoom platform for the students pursuing B.Sc. Forensic
         Science programme at Kristu Jayanti College. The guest lecture

         commenced at 9:30 AM, and there were about 138 participants

         who actively took part in the meeting.




         Questioned document examination is a major forensic discipline

         that involves the forensic examination of document writings, sig-

         natures, handwriting, printed documents, security documents,
         and many more to identify instances of fraud and cheating. Ex-

         emplars are used to compare questioned writing, and the ques-

         tioned document expert is able to distinguish between genuine

         writing, forgery, simulated forgery, tracing, manipulated hand-

         writing, etc. It is a field that relies on the skill of the forensic

         examiner, and students had a good opportunity to understand
         questioned  document  examination  from  a  trained  expert  using

         different case experiences during the guest lecture.

         The resource person shared his knowledge in the examination of

         questioned documents and the practical approaches in this field.

         He also covered various topics related to questioned document

         examination, including:
         •  What is a document?




                                                            26]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[•  Different types of forgery
         •  Forged signature with case study and specimen

         •  Alterations, erasures/abrasions in documents with case studies

         •  Different techniques used for the examination of forged doc-

            uments

         •  Examination of digital and typewritten documents

         •  The application of forensic linguists to solve the cases



         During the question & answer session, students raised their

         doubts related to the examination of documents.

         The  entire session  was  innovative  and helped the  students  to

         learn more about the practical approaches to the examination

         of questioned documents.




























































                                                           27]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[IN-HOUSE CAREER ORIENTATION



                                                 SESSION








         A career orientation session on “Career and prospects in Foren-

         sic Science” was organized for the second and third-year B.Sc.

         Forensic  Science  students on  24.02.2022  from  09:00  AM  to

         12:00 PM through the Zoom platform.  The resource persons

         were:

         1. Mr. Don Caeiro, Assistant Professor and Programme

            Coordinator, Forensic Science Programme, Kristu Jayanti
            College, Bangalore

         2. Mr. Jeremiah Justus. M, Assistant Professor, Kristu Jayanti

            College, Bangalore

         3. Ms. Chetna  Tidke, Assistant Professor, Kristu Jayanti College,

            Bangalore

         4. Dr. Shayani Ghosh, Assistant Professor, Kristu Jayanti
            College, Bangalore




         The session was initiated by Mr. Don Caeiro, Assistant Profes-

         sor, Forensic Science, at Kristu Jayanti College (Autonomous),

         Bengaluru. The session was focused on making decisions about

         higher education after earning a Bachelor’s degree in the field of
         forensics.  The importance of drafting a plan, making accurate

         inquiries about one’s university/institute of choice, and how to

         filter out the right course of our interest by researching about the

         universities and the schemes that are promised by the same was

         the highlight of the session. Mr. Don Caeiro not only restricted

         his knowledge to Indian institutions but also gave a brief idea

         about the various courses offered in the line of forensics at uni-
         versities overseas. Keeping in mind that the field of Forensic Sci-

         ence is newly established in many educational institutions,





                                                             28]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[Mr. Don Caeiro pointed out the categories of universities based

         on rankings, affiliations, reputations, and mainly, the financial

         needs of a student meeting the choice of program for Masters.




         The second session was taken up by Mr. Jeremiah Justus. M,

         Assistant Professor, Forensic Science, at Kristu Jayanti College

         (Autonomous), Bengaluru.  The session was about the different
         roles and designations that one could take up in the field of fo-

         rensic science. Opportunities promised in public as well as pri-

         vate  sectors were  brought into  the picture. Many  public agen-

         cies like CBI (Central Bureau of Investigation), IB (Intelligfence

         Bureau), Anti-doping officials, etc., were mentioned. A statisti-

         cal overview of job distribution over the years was presented in
         order to have a better understanding of the advancement in this

         branch. Sir  provided a reference for doing our own search for

         job opportunities and learning the various rules that are a man-

         date for any career aspirant. Mr. Jeremiah plotted a road map

         that  showed the steps  that  we can  take  to ensure a  systematic

         study about the objectives we need in attaining efficiency in the
         path of establishing a professional career - To be an early plan-

         ner, invoking the spirit of competitiveness, applying in multiple

         firms, etc.

         Ms. Chetna Tidke initiated the third session by briefing the par-

         ticipants about the different All India Level examinations that

         are conducted pertaining to forensic science. Eligibility criteria

         were discussed, the qualifying percentage and interview round
         for various exams were mentioned, and the possibility of being

         recruited in the Central and State Forensic Science Laboratories

         as a Forensic Professional were discussed.  The question paper

         pattern and syllabus covered in each section of the paper for

         the comprehensive aptitude tests of postgraduate students were

         brought up. The paper pattern discussed was:





                                                             29]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[•  Section A: 50 questions
         •  Section B: 70 questions

         •  Type of questions: Objective and one marker

         •  Duration of exam: 2 hours




         Ma’am also threw light on the eligibility criteria for postgradu-

         ates for FACT (Forenisc Aptitude and Caliber  Test)/ FACT Plus/

         NET  (National  Eligibility  Test)/GATE  (Gaduate  Aptitude  Test
         in Engineering)/GPAT (Graduate Pharmacy Aptitude Test).




         The final session handled by Dr. Shayani Ghosh mainly focussed

         on  how to  get  enrolled  in Ph.D. and  what  are the advantages,

         qualifying criteria, the current syllabus, and paper pattern, and

         how to prepare for the same. Attaining a doctorate in the field

         that one specializes in determines the eligibility for an Assistant
         Professorship, Junior Research Fellowship, or both. Qualifying

         criteria for both general and reserved category according to the

         UGC (University Grants Commission) was put to light by Dr.

         Shayani.  The current  paper  pattern,  as discussed by  ma’am, is

         as follows:
         •  Paper 1: 50 questions (general paper)

         •  Paper 2: 100 questions (related to the core subject)

         •  Duration: 3 hours

         •  Qualifying  marks:  General  category  -  40%  and  Reserved  cat-

            egory - 35%

         Preparation for the test can begin during the first semester of

         the M.Sc. A student can appear for the exam during the third
         semester of the master’s program. Ma’am also mentioned the

         advantages of qualifying NET and JRF in the career path of a

         student. Dr. Shayani was kind enough to give us insights into the

         various institutions (public and private) that promised a Ph.D.

         program in their curriculum.






                                                             30]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[GUEST LECTURE ON THE ROLE



                         OF FORENSIC MEDICINE IN


                               CRIME INVESTIGATION







         A guest lecture on the topic “Role of Forensic Medicine in Crime

         Investigation” was conducted on 26th February 2022, at 9:30

         AM by the Department of Forensic Science, Kristu Jayanti Col-
         lege.  Dr.  Hareesh  S  Gouda,  Professor  and  Head,  Department  of

         Forensic  Medicine, Father  Muller  Medical  College,  Mangalore,

         was the resource person for the session. The program was con-

         ducted over the Zoom platform for the students pursuing B.Sc.

         Forensic Science programme at Kristu Jayanti College. The guest

         lecture commenced at 9:30 AM, and there were about 127 par-

         ticipants who actively took part in the meeting.



         The resource person is presently working as Professor and also

         serves as a Head of the Department of Forensic Medicine at

         Father Muller Medical College, Mangalore. He has 18 years

         of experience in teaching and handling medico-legal cases. Dr.

         Hareesh has published in numerous national and international

         journals. He has also authored and contributed chapters to text-
         books of Forensic Medicine.

         The  resource  person  gave  the  students  new  knowledge  about

         the workings of Forensic Medicine and how coroners with the

         knowledge  of  medicine  and  law  help  in  various  reaching  con-

         clusions in investigations. He also gave explanations about cer-

         tain terminologies in Forensic Medicine. He spoke about the

         history of Forensic Medicine. Dr. Hareesh also explained the
         workings of Forensic Medicine by talking about various cases he

         has worked on. He gave a detailed explanation about different

         wounds, how they are caused, and how they help in concluding

         the case because of their nature.



                                                             31]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[The entire session was interesting and provided students an in-
         sight into Forensic Medicine, autopsy, and other pathological

         examinations which are used to aid medico-legal cases and in-

         vestigations.






















































































                                                             32]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[GUEST LECTURE ON DISASTER



                             VICTIM IDENTIFICATION







         A  guest  lecture  on  the  topic “Disaster Victim  Identification”  was

         conducted on 13th May 2022, at 3 PM in M3 Auditorium, Main

         Block, Kristu Jayanti College, Bangalore.  The resource person

         for the session was Dr. Deepak  V, Asst. Professor and Forensic

         Consultant, Forensic Odontology, M R Ambedkar Dental Col-

         lege & Hospital, Bangalore.



         Disaster Victim Identification is not a crime-based scenario, but

         the techniques of forensic science are very much applied to this

         area. Anthropological analysis, DNA (Deoxyribonucleic acid)

         analysis, and odontological analysis are among the many ap-

         proaches toward Disaster Victim Identification.




         Dr. Deepak listed the many avenues where forensic expertise
         is required for Disaster  Victim Identification. He explained the

         need for closure to the relatives and how this field of humanitar-

         ian forensics is a deed-based field that requires commitment and

         fulfilment.  He  motivated  the  students  using  case  studies  of  the

         recent past and expressed that they must work hard to achieve

         their dreams in the field and promised better scenarios to emerge

         in the future.
         The session concluded with questions from the students, and the

         resource person patiently and clearly explained the doubts.





















                                                             33]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[International Conference on
                                    Adavnacement in Forensic Science




























                                        A snapshot from Inquisitor





























                                        A snapshot of Cyber Forensics

                                                  Expert Lecture


                                                            34]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[A snapshot from Atrium






























                       Guest Lecture on Questioned Document Examination
































                                   In-House Career Orientation Session


                                                             35]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[Guest Lecture on Role of Forensic

                                     Medicine in Crime Investigations






























                                                 Guest Lecture on

                                        Disaster Victim Identification






























                                                             36]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[INDUSTRIAL VISITS






































                                         JSS Medical College, Mysore













































                                               Axxonet, Bangalore






                                                             37]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[-























                                 RESEARCH ARTICLES












          •  Detection of hidden files and finding out its hiding mecha-
             nism

          •  Effect of stereotypes on the identification of criminals

          •  Detection of pesticides in common fruits or vegetables

             available in different regions of bangalore city

          •  A study to identify commonly employed methods of dis-

             guise
          •  A study to estimate the extent of inefficacy of existing pre-

             sumptive tests on blood stains contaminated with common

             contaminants encountered in southern india

          •  To contrive artificial blood for use in demonstration of

             blood pattern analysis

          •  Appropriate steps a forensic scientist should follow at the
             scene of crime























                                                             38]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[DETECTION OF HIDDEN


                        FILES AND FINDING OUT ITS



                                 HIDDEN MECHANISM









        Ms. Jocelyn Kunju John

        Ms. Catherine Maria Johny

        Mr. Thomas Prince Kuruppen Parambil


        Mr. Justin Babu



         INTRODUCTION

         Digital forensics, on a broad spectrum, can be defined

         as a complete understanding and analysis of digital data

         present on the computer or laptop. Digital forensics can

         also be explained as the investigation of digital     artefacts
         from the scene of the crime for certain facts and informa-

         tion. It deals with the recovery of legal evidence within

         the digital devices and the digital storage media. The pro-

         cedure is carried out by the usage of digital tools, which

         enables us to retrieve the  desired information. Imaging is

         a technique where the bit-by-bit storage space along with

         the data present in the device is replicated onto another
         device. The suspect device is not used for further analysis,

         but its image file is used.





         AIM AND OBJECTIVES OF THE STUDY

         •To determine the hidden data in a device.

         •To understand the mechanism behind the hidden data and
         thus deduce a technique to recognize the same.

         •To identify and study if the already existing tools could

         detect the hidden data within the computer system.




                                                             39]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[METHODOLOGY

               An external storage device (SanDisk Cruzer Blade Pen drive)
               was formatted using the New Technology File System (NTFS).

               Ten files with different file extensions were selected and cop-

               ied onto the USB device.

               The 10 files of different file formats were as follows:

               1. .AVI

               2. .DOC

               3. .DOCX
               4. .MP3

               5. .MP4

               6. .PDF

               7. .PNG

               8. .JPEG

               9. .WAV

               10..TXT
               Using different hiding methods, such as lockdir, lockbox,

               etc.,  the data were  hidden,  which  was followed  by subject-

               ing the pen drive to the imaging process in order to find the

               hidden data.



               FINDINGS

               From the study, it could be concluded that using imaging
               tools, it is possible to find the hidden data.

               With  the  properties  hiding  method  and  hiding  using  differ-

               ent software, the files were detected without modifications

               to the metadata and hash values.

               With the file signature and file extension change, there was a

               change in the metadata as well as the hash value.

               The file signature detected in the image file was not of the
               original file format but the one that was changed to. When

               the details of the files are checked, the details correspond to



                                                             40]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[the details of the original file format. This proves that the file

         has been altered.

         Hence, no matter what the data is or how it is hidden by cy-

         bercriminals, it can be recovered and used as court evidence.























                            Fig 1. AccessData FTK Imager screenshot

























                                  Fig2. Hex Editor Neo screenshot























                       Fig 3. AccessData FTK Imager identifying the

                                             hidden PDF file.



                                                             41]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[REFERENCES:

               •  Guo, R.,  Wu, F., Li,  Y., Zhu, R., & Sheng, K. (2015).  The

                  information hiding mechanism based on compressed doc-

                  ument format. International Journal Of Computing Sci-

                  ence And Mathematics, 6(1), 97. Retrieved from https://
                  doi.org/10.1504/ijcsm.2015.067547

               •  Cao, F., Qian, X., & An, B. (2020). Low-complexity re-

                  versible data hiding in encrypted image via MSB hierar-

                  chical coding and LSB compression. Multimedia Systems,

                  27(3),  317-330.  Retrieved  from  https://doi.org/10.1007/

                  s00530-020-00700-6

               •  Hassan,  N.  A.,  & Hijazi,  R.  (2017). Data hiding tech-
                  niques in Windows OS. Syngress, 2, 23-43.

               •  Upguard.com. 2022.  What is Digital Forensics? | Up-

                  Guard. [online] Retrieved from https://www.upguard.

                  com/blog/digital-forensics. [Accessed 13 April 2022]

               •  EasyTechJunkie. 2022.  What Is a File Signature? (with

                  picture). [online] Retrieved from https://www.easytech-

                  junkie.com/what-is-a-file-signature.htm.                             [Accessed           13
                  April 2022].









                                             DID YOU KNOW?




                                             Which crime lab unit is responsible for

                                             examining body fluids and organs for the

                                             presence of drugs and poisons?




                                             Answer: Toxicology Unit









                                                             42]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[EFFECT OF STEREOTYPES



                             ON THE IDENTIFICATION


                                          OF CRIMINALS









        Ms. Aakanksha Sunil

        Ms. Adheena Shibu

        Ms. Ann Mariya Thomas

        Ms. Lorraine Tissan

        Mr. Sharath Richard




        INTRODUCTION

        Stereotypes are preconceived and prejudiced notions that we
        form  which can  help  us  access and categorize information

        in our brain easily. While  stereotypes help in facilitating in-

        formation processing, they can also interfere with forming

        judgements which can lead to and inaccurate decisions. In

        the judicial arena, there have been incidents where someone
        was wrongfully accused of committing a crime due to un-

        derlying prejudices such as race and gender.  This research

        focused on the study of society’s perception of criminals.




        AIM

        This study aimed to determine if any visual characteristics

        found in suspects can be stereotypically used by people/sys-
        tems to define criminals and whether factors like the type

        of crime and physical appearance/traits of the criminal can

        influence the subject’s decision.

        The study also aimed to see if certain demographic factors

        of the subject like their age, gender, and occupational status

        would influence their perception of a criminal.




                                                             43]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[METHODOLOGY

               For this study, a questionnaire was prepared which entailed

               10 hypothetical case studies that were based on 5 types

               of crime – murder, drug trafficking, sexual assault, money

               laundering, and hacking.  The case studies were followed

               by a photo line-up which had the images of 2 suspects pro-
               vided to the subjects, in which one fit the stereotype of

               a criminal of that type of crime while the other did not.

               A link was generated, and the questionnaire was distrib-

               uted via the social media platform. People of various age

               groups and occupational backgrounds were provided with

               the questionnaire for collecting responses. A total of 318

               responses were collected and analyzed. The responses were
               segregated and arranged based on different parameters and

               the  results  were  tabulated.  Pie  charts  and  bar  graphs  that

               showed the distribution of responses based on different pa-

               rameters were generated using MS Excel.




               OBSERVATIONS

               Findings showed that an individual’s stereotype about a
               criminal can vary depending on the type of crime given.

               The  study  also  showed  that  other  factors  like  age,  race,

               and sex of the suspect can also trigger stereotypes affiliated

               with a criminal of that particular type of crime. For exam-

               ple, one of the hypothetical scenarios given was a house-

               hold poisoning case where a man was found dead on his

               couch because of poisoning. The suspect line-up provided
               was that of two suspects, one male, and the other female.

               The majority of the participant pool chose the female to be

               the probable suspect and from this response, we learned

               that people  often associate crimes like poisoning with fe-

               males stereotypically.


                                                             44]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[CONCLUSION

        Further in this study, after observing the results we were

        able to conclude that demographic factors of the subjects

        like their age, gender, and occupational status did not have
        any significant impact on their choice of suspect in each

        case study/scenario that was provided.

        Ultimately, this study was done to show that an individ-

        ual can  hold  such stereotypes unconsciously and  these

        stereotypes can influence the person’s decision-mak-

        ing.


        REFERENCES:

        •  Davis,  P.  (2016).  Perceptions  of  Criminality: An  Experi-

            ment on Race, Class, and Gender Stereotypes.

        •  Osborne, D., & Davies, P. G. (2013). Eyewitness iden-

            tifications are affected by stereotypes about a suspect’s

            level  of  perceived stereotypical.  Group  Processes  & In-

            tergroup Relations, 16(4), 488-504.
        •  Smalarz, L., Madon, S.,  Yang,  Y., Guyll, M., & Buck, S.

            (2016).  The perfect match: Do criminal stereotypes bias

            forensic evidence analysis? Law and Human Behaviour,

            40(4), 420.

        •  Mcleod,  S.,  2022.  Stereotypes  |  Simply  Psychology.

            [online] Simplypsychology.org. Retrieved from https://

            www.simplypsychology.org/katz-braly.html  [Accessed
            13 April 2022].




















                                                             45]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[DETECTION OF PESTICIDES



                             IN COMMON FRUITS OR



                         VEGETABLES AVAILABLE IN



                             DIFFERENT REGIONS OF



                                     BANGALORE CITY








                                                                           Ms. Gayathri L Nair

                                                                           Ms. Amulya M


                INTRODUCTION

                Toxicology is primarily concerned with the study of the

                harmful consequences that any physical, chemical, or bio-

                logical agent may have on humans, animals,  and the envi-

                ronment in general. Forensic toxicology, a subdivision of
                toxicology, focuses on the utilization of regular toxicolog-

                ical methods and procedures to aid in the medico-legal ex-

                amination of cases involving death, poisoning, and drug

                abuse. It includes analyzing numerous biological samples

                such as blood, urine, and other bodily fluids to detect the
                presence of any toxin, as well as individualizing the toxin

                discovered  and  determining  the  amount  of  toxin  present

                in the individual’s system. Among the toxins usually en-

                countered are pesticides that are used to deter pest infes-

                tation in crops. These pesticides can cause serious health

                issues in the individuals who are exposed to them, which

                include confusion, lack of appetite, disorientation, and
                much more.




                OBJECTIVE

                The objective of this study was to detect the possible pres-

                ence of pesticides in the vegetables and fruits available in


                                                             46]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[different regions of Bangalore city as well as in the ones

         purchased through online platforms by performing  Thin

         Layer Chromatography or  TLC. Five different vegetables

         and fruits were chosen, which included cabbage, carrot,

         tomato, grape, and spinach. Sample collection was done
         by dividing the city into four main regions, North, South,

         East, and West. A prominent online grocery shopping plat-

         form was also  chosen along with these regions.  The col-

         lected samples were then extracted by grinding their peels

         in a mortar and pestle in the presence of a hexane-  acetone

         mixture. Since the control carbofuran pesticide was avail-

         able in the granular form, extraction was carried out for
         carbofuran as well by grinding them in a mortar and pestle

         in the presence of methanol. The extraction was then fol-

         lowed  by  the  preparation  of  the  TLC  chambers  for  which

         two different solvent systems were used as the control pes-

         ticides  (hexane-acetone  for  malathion  and  hexane-chloro-

         form-ethyl acetate-acetone for carbofuran).

         While the prepared chambers were left for saturation, the
         spotting  was  done  on the  TLC plates using microcapillary

         tubes. The spots of the vegetable and fruit samples, along

         with the standard pesticide sample, were placed  equidistant

         from each other on the spotting line, marked approximate-

         ly 1 cm above the base of the plate. The spots were allowed

         to  dry,  after  which  the plates  were carefully placed  in the

         respective chambers.  The  TLC was run for 15-20 minutes,
         which was sufficient for the solvent to cover 80% of the

         run, after which visualization was done using  Tollen’s re-

         agent  (for  malathion)  and  alkaline  Fast  Blue  B  reagent  (for

         carbofuran). Spot formation was observed and the distance

         traveled by them was measured and used to calculate the

         Rf (Retention factor) values (ratio of the distance traveled



                                                            47]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[the solute to the distance traveled by the solvent) obtained

                for the vegetable and fruit samples which were then com-

                pared to the Rf of the standard pesticides and the results

                were interpreted.  The values obtained were tabulated ac-

                cording to their regions.


                RESULTS

                The observations indicated that the Rf values of samples

                that were tested for the presence of carbofuran correspond-

                ed with the Rf values of the standard pesticide samples,

                indicating the possible presence of the pesticide in them.

                While the samples that were tested for malathion did not
                give  results  or  values  that  corresponded  to  the  value  ob-

                tained  for  the  standard  pesticide.  Since  TLC  is  a  screen-

                ing method, sophisticated techniques such as GC-MS (Gas

                Chromatography-Mass Spectrometry)  may be  used  for  the

                confirmation and quantification of pesticides in vegetable

                and fruit samples.


                REFERENCES:

                •  Mishra,  A. (2020,  April 10).  Chapter: Forensic Chem-

                   istry and  Toxicology. Forensic Chemistry and  Toxicol-

                   ogy. Retrieved from https://www.intechopen.com/chap-

                   ters/71742

                •  Abbott, D. C., Burridge, A. S.,  Thomson, J., &  Webb, K.

                   S. (1967). A thin-layer chromatographic screening test
                   for organophosphorus  pesticide residues.  The Analyst,


















                                                            48]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA[A STUDY TO IDENTIFY


                             COMMONLY EMPLOYED



                             METHODS OF DISGUISE










           Ms. Krishnapriya

           Ms. Litzia Sebastian

           Ms. Nivya George




         INTRODUCTION

         Disguised handwriting is the willful modification of a per-

         son’s natural writing to conceal the identity. When a person

         is called to give his handwriting sample for investigation,
         he /she tends to disguise the handwriting to conceal their

         identity. Disguised  writing  is  always superficial and  leads

         to an inferior quality of writing. According to the princi-

         ple of handwriting, individual characteristics remain con-

         stant.  Individuals change their class characteristics to dis-

         guise their handwriting, and the individual characteristics

         will  not  change.  Common  methods  of  disguised  writing  in-
         clude change of style of writing, change of pen pressure,

         change of slant, use of unskilled hand, change of pictorial

         effects, change of shading and spacing, change of line qual-

         ity, presence of pen pause, tremors, and hesitation, change

         of diacritics, etc.



         AIM AND OBJECTIVES OF THE STUDY
         •  To distinguish the disguised handwriting from the origi-

             nal handwriting

         •  To find the methods used for disguising the handwriting

         •  To determine the commonly used methods for the disguise



                                                             49]]></page><page Index="51"><![CDATA[of handwriting

              •  To calculate the percentage of each method used for dis-

                  guising the handwriting



              METHODOLOGY
              1. Sample collection and procedure

              •  The samples were collected from 100 subjects aged be-

                  tween 17 to 25 years.

              •  The subjects were asked to write on an A4 white sheet of

                  paper using a ball blue pen. The paper and pen were pro-

                  vided by the researchers to the subjects
              •  The subjects are restricted from looking into other writing

                  while giving the standard and disguised writing sample and

                  to use any other pen, paper, and other supporting materials

                  like paper, books, or writing pads under the A4 sheet.

              •  Subjects were selected with fewer external factors that af-

                  fect the writing. They were instructed not to use their un-
                  skilled hand to disguise writing

              •  A control passage was dictated to the subjects.

              •  The following samples were collected from each of the sub-

                  jects – 1. Standard handwriting (slow speed), 2. Standard

                  handwriting  (moderate  speed)  and  3.  Disguised  handwrit-

                  ing.

              •  The subjects were asked to take as much time as they want-
                  ed to disguise the writing.

              •  The 3 samples collected from each subject were considered

                  as one sample for comparison.

              •  15 characteristics were fixed to compare in the samples

              •  A comparison between the disguised handwriting with the

                  original handwriting was performed.

              •  The changes in the 15 characteristics in the sample were
                  recorded in a table.




                                                             50]]></page><page Index="52"><![CDATA[•  The commonly used methods of disguise were observed

            and recorded

        The 15 characters which were looked for and graded were:

        1. Style of writing – changed / same

        2. Spacing between words – increased/decreased/same

        3. Slant – changed / same

        4. Alignment – changed / same
        5. Pen lifts – present/ absent

        6. Pen pause – present/absent

        7. Pen pressure –    increased/ decreased/ same

        8. Interlineation – increased/ decreased/ same

        9. Size of letters – increased/ decreased/ same

        10. Line quality – changed/ same

        11. Hesitation – present/ absent
        12. Tremors – present/ absent

        13. Pictorial effects – present/ absent

        14. Font style of numbers  – changed/ same

        15. Symbols – changed/ same



         FINDINGS






































                                                            51]]></page><page Index="53"><![CDATA[•  70 people changed their pen pressure and only 10 peo-
                    ple changed or used the symbols in disguised writing

                •  Most people increased or decreased their pen pressure

                    along with other methods of disguise.

                •  The subjects used more than one method while disguis-

                    ing.

                •  15 out of 100 subjects used more than 8 methods of

                    disguise.
                •  19 subjects out of 100 only used 3 and a lesser number

                    of methods of disguise.

                • 66 subjects out of 100 used 4 to 8 methods to disguise

                writing.




                REFERENCES:

                •  Disguised handwriting. (1987, November 1). Sci-
                    enceDirect. Retrieved from https://www.sciencedirect.

                    com/science/article/abs/pii/S0015736887727868?via

                    %3Dihub










                                                             52]]></page><page Index="54"><![CDATA[•  Most people increased or decreased their pen pres-

              sure along with J. Harris, J. (1953). Disguised hand-
              writing. Journal of Criminal Law and Criminology,

              43(5),685–689. Retrieved from https://scholarlycom-

              mons.law.northwestern.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?arti-

              cle=4076&context=jclc#:~:text=Disguised%20hand-

              writing%20is%20the%20willful,the%20purpose%20

              of%20concealing%20identity.&text=Most%20laymen-

              %20have%20the%20classic,and%20in%20some%20
              anonymous%20letters

           •  Bird, C. (2010, September 1). Forensic Document Ex-

              aminers’ Skill in Distinguishing Between Natural and

              Disguised Handwriting Behaviors.  Wiley Online Li-

              brary. Retrieved from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/

              doi/abs/10.1111/j.1556-4029.2010.01456.x

           •  C.W.P.L.-T.,          R.K.C.A.,         H.W.H.L.,          M.H.Y.C.,           L.W.L.C.,
              & G.M.T.L. (2010, 28 October). Handwriting charac-

              teristics among secondary students with and without

              physical  disabilities:  A  study  with  a  computerized  tool.

              Research in Developmental Disabilities. Retrieved from

              https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/

              S089142221000226X

           •  Konstantinidis, S. (1987). Disguised handwriting.
              Journal of the Forensic Science Society, 27(6), 383–

              392. Retrieved from https://doi.org/10.1016/s0015-

              7368(87)72786-8




















                                                            53]]></page><page Index="55"><![CDATA[A STUDY TO ESTIMATE



                        THE EXTENT OF INEFFICACY



                         OF EXISTING PRESUMPTIVE



                    TESTS ON BLOOD STAINS CON-


                       TAMINATED WITH COMMON



                         CONTAMINANTS ENCOUN-



                        TERED IN SOUTHERN INDIA













                                                                  Ms. Umme Salma Razak

                                                                  Ms. Aishwarya P.V

                                                                  Ms. Arya K.S

                                                                  Mr. Neeraj P.B

                                                                  Mr. Joseph J. Kachappally



               INTRODUCTION

               Blood is the most common evidence in crimes and is many a

               times crucial in fixing the corpus delicti, proving the modus

               operandi and also the actus reus during a crime. Presump-

               tive testing of suspected blood stains is the first step in the
               forensic examination of blood. Presumptive tests are usu-

               ally performed at the scene of the crime and form the basis

               on which a stain is collected for further examination in the

               FSL. The common presumptive tests performed for identi-

               fication of blood are Benzidine and Kastle Meyer tests.

               Even though the efficacy of presumptive tests is highly reli-

               able, in the presence of certain contaminants, their efficacy




                                                            54]]></page><page Index="56"><![CDATA[is altered. In South India, the common practise of using

          beautifying skin and hair additives is predominantly ob-
          served. This study attempts to identify the extent to which

          common contaminants, namely turmeric, kumkum, and

          coconut oil, reduce the efficacy of the presumptive tests

          (Benzidine and Kastle Meyer tests) for blood.



          OBJECTIVE

          •  To identify if contaminants (turmeric, kumkum, and co-
              conut oil) have a negative impact on the performance of

              the presumptive tests, Benzidine and Kastle Meyer Tests,

              used for forensic identification of dried blood stains.

          •  To identify how many among the three contaminants

              (turmeric,  kumkum,  and  coconut  oil),  have  a  negative

              impact on the presumptive tests.

          •  To identify if the negative impact on the presumptive
              tests is quantifiable.




          METHODOLOGY

          To analyse the effect of each of the contaminants on the pre-

          sumptive tests, the entire study was split into three phases:




          Phase 1 – Conceptualization
          In this phase, attempts were made to test contaminated

          blood in increasing concentrations of the 3 different con-

          taminants. The threshold concentration at which each con-

          taminant gave a false negative result for each presumptive

          test was identified in this phase.

          Blood was serially diluted up to the 6th dilution, and the

          specific contaminant was added to each of the 6 dilutions
          in the following concentrations and tested against Benzi-




                                                            55]]></page><page Index="57"><![CDATA[dine and Kastle Meyer tests separately.


















               The results were as follows:



               It was decided to discontinue the use of the Kastle Mayer

               test for turmeric and kumkum contaminants as they gave

               false positive results even in the absence of blood.

               However, in the case of coconut oil, both Benzidine and

               Kastle Mayer tests were performed.



































               Phase 2 – Replication

               In this phase, the identified threshold concentration of con-

               tamination was prepared, and the presumptive tests were

               performed 30 times to check the accuracy of the findings.






                                                            56]]></page><page Index="58"><![CDATA[In all the replicated attempts, the result proved to be the
         same - negative for blood.




         Phase 3 – Validation:

         In this  phase, the  findings  were statistically analysed to

         identify the validity of the identified results.

         As the results in all the replicated attempts were found to

         be false negative, the need for statistical validation was ab-
         sent.



         FINDINGS

         •  When turmeric was used as a contaminant, it was found

             that the Benzidine test did not detect the presence of blood

             in a dilution mixture of Blood – 0.025 ml% + Contami-

             nant – 4g% and above.
         •  When kumkum was used as a contaminant, it was found

             that the Benzidine test did not detect the presence of blood

             in a dilution mixture of Blood – 0.025 ml% + Contami-

             nant – 4g% and above.

         •  The Kastle Meyer test could not be interpreted as the pink
             colour was due to interference of turmeric and kumkum

             (false positive results were noted in the presence of trace

             amounts of turmeric and kumkum).

         •  When coconut oil was  used as a  contaminant, it  was

             found that the Benzidine test did not detect the presence

             of blood in a dilution mixture of Blood – 0.00625 ml%+



                                                            57]]></page><page Index="59"><![CDATA[•  Contaminant – 4g% and above.

               •  When kumkum was used as a contaminant, it was found
                   that the Benzidine test did not detect the presence of blood

                   in a dilution mixture of Blood – 0.025 ml% + Contami-

                   nant – 4g% and above.

               •  The Kastle Meyer test could not be interpreted as the pink

                   colour was due to interference of turmeric and kumkum
                   (false positive results were noted in the presence of trace

                   amounts of turmeric and kumkum).

               •  When coconut oil was  used as a  contaminant, it  was

                   found that the Benzidine test did not detect the presence

                   of blood in a dilution mixture of Blood – 0.00625 ml%

                   + Contaminant – 4ml% and above, and the Kastle Mey-

                   er test did not detect the presence of blood in a dilu-
                   tion mixture of Blood – 0.00125 ml% + Contaminant

                   – 4ml% and above.




               CONCLUSION

               In  cases  where  scientific  evidence  was  heavily  relied  on,

               false  positive/false  negative  results  can  be  of  major  con-

               cern. They can lead to a rampant rate of acquittal.



               Presumptive tests are relied on by field scientific officers to

               decide whether the evidence needs to be collected and for-

               warded to the Forensic Science Laboratories.  When these

               tests provide false positive/false negative results, this can

               adversely affect the progress of the investigation.



               This study addresses the extent to which common contam-

               inants  can  lead  to  a  false  interpretation  of  the  commonly

               used presumptive tests. This study can be a basis on which

               a more extensive study can be performed to understand the



                                                             58]]></page><page Index="60"><![CDATA[impact of these contaminants as well as similar contami-

          nants on presumptive tests at large.


           REFERENCES

          •  Nilsson, A. (2006).  The forensic luminol test for blood:

              unwanted interference and the effect on subsequent

              analysis.  The Swedish  National  Laboratory of  Foren-
              sic Science (SKL). Retrieved from http://www.themur-

              derofmeredithkercher.net/docupl/filelibrary/docs/

              forensics/2006-06-09                      -Study-Nilsson-Luminol-Test-In-

              terference-and-Effect-on-Analysis.pdf

          •  Castelló, A., Francés, F., &  Verdú, F. (2009). Bleach in-

              terference in forensic luminol tests on porous surfac-

              es: More about the drying time effect.  Talanta, 77(4),
              1555–1557. Retrieved from https://doi.org/10.1016/j.

              talanta.2008.09.008.

          •  Kasthuri Bai, D.,  Visalakshi, A., Amutha, L. C., & Shan-

              mukham, B. (2007).  Turmeric Interference in  Trap Case.

              In Proceedings of 18th All India Forensic Science Con-

              ference - 2007 (pp. 4484–4492). Directorate of Forensic

              Science Services, New Delhi.
          •  Fukushima, A. R., Bernardo Fonseca, R. I., Ricci, E.

              L., Spinosa, H. D. S., Bernardi, M. M., de Abreu, G.

              R.,  Waziry, P. A. F.,  Nicoletti, M. A., Ambrosio, S.

              R., de Araujo, I. P., & Munoz, J.  W. P. (2019). Actual

              trends in the use of the kastle-meyer test: applications

              in different species and verification of the limit of de-

              tection  of  sensitivity  and  vestigiality.  Journal  of  Dairy,
              Veterinary  &  Animal  Research,  8(4).  Retrieved  from

              https://doi.org/10.15406/jdvar.2019.08.00261.

          •  Tobe, S. S., Watson, N., & Daéid, N. N. (2007). Evalu-

              ation of Six Presumptive Tests for Blood, Their



                                                            59]]></page><page Index="61"><![CDATA[Specificity, Sensitivity, and Effect on High Molecu-

                lar-Weight DNA. Journal of Forensic Sciences, 52(1),
                102–109.             Retrieved            from          https://doi.org/10.1111/

                j.15564029.2006.00324.x.

























                                           DID YOU KNOW?




                                           Bugs can help solve a crime. It’s actually

                                           called forensic entomology.  While bugs

                                           can’t actually solve a crime, investigators
                                           are able to look inside of an insect’s (typ-

                                           ically  a  maggot)  stomach  and  is  able  to

                                           determine how long a body has been de-

                                           composing.

































                                                            60]]></page><page Index="62"><![CDATA[TO CONTRIVE ARTIFICIAL



                                   BLOOD FOR USE IN


                      DEMONSTRATION OF BLOOD



                                   PATTERN ANALYSIS











          Ms. Sruthi Evangeline Kali

          Ms. Harshitha M V

          Ms. Faiza Farheen

          Mr. Fahed Bin Abdul Aziz K



          INTRODUCTION

          Blood pattern analysis is the concept of blood behaviour
          which acts in a unique and different way when it is forced

          to emerge. It deals with the interpretation of bloodstains at

          the crime scene to recreate the caused bloodshed. It helps

          the  investigator  in drawing  conclusions about  the  modus

          operandi, nature and the timing of crime, the direction of

          attack, the angle of attack, the probable distance between

          the victim and assailant, nature of force, nature of weap-
          on, number of blows, the position of the suspect and the

          victim, description of the perpetrator such as height, which

          hand was used, the approximate time of crime commit-

          ted, mens rea and actus reus, manner of crime like violent

          crime, act of defence, etc, and the sequence of events can

          be determined which eventually leads to the reconstruction

          of  the crime.  This  happens  because  of  the properties  of
          blood. Blood has different properties such as viscosity, in-

          ertia, surface tension, as their physical characteristics and

          it also shows biological properties such as vascular spasm,




                                                            61]]></page><page Index="63"><![CDATA[platelet  plug,  and  clotting  or  agglutination.  The  compo-

               sition of blood also plays a role in blood spatter.  They

               altogether  play  a  prominent  role in  deciding the  spatter.

               And also, blood has a changing behaviour due to various

               factors and circumstances like velocity, pressure, force,

               weapon, surface, height, angles, etc. All these aspects are

               combined  and studied in  relation to each  other and this
               study is called blood pattern analysis which is emerging as

               a vast subject in forensic science by playing a role in help-

               ing to solve a crime. Hence the examination of blood is vi-

               tal in blood pattern analysis as well as academic research

               studies. For academic purposes, blood is hardly used be-
               cause blood  has its own problems such as  both animal

               blood and human blood are expensive, have low market-

               ability, i.e., rarely available to buy, blood decomposes; it

               is hazardous in nature causing blood poisoning and HIV

               (Human Immunodeficiency Virus), etc.

               It has an offensive smell that could be intolerable to many

               and blood lysed with time and agglutinates which leads
               to  false  results  in analysis. Hence academic  and research

               studies cannot always rely on blood. And for this reason,

               many institutions, organisations, and scientists have for-

               mulated alternatives for blood.  Theatrical blood was the

               most used blood, and this can be easily prepared by in-

               ternet formulations. But they failed as they showed clots,

               pools, scales etc. And later, standard substitutes were for-
               mulated and got approved to only meet a few properties of

               blood. There is no current theatrical blood as such. How-

               ever, NFBS, oxycyte, Awlata dye, and Millington substi-

               tutes are available and suitable for blood pattern analysis

               but the problem is, all of them are very expensive.






                                                            62]]></page><page Index="64"><![CDATA[METHODOLOGY

          So, the present study was conducted to develop a forensic

          blood substitute that is similar to human blood and of low

          cost. The objectives of this study are to develop an alterna-

          tive of blood in a simpler way with few components which

          are cheap and also to validate their suitability for blood

          pattern  analysis.  The  methodology  of  this  study  was  de-
          signed in three steps. They are

          •Preliminary development

          •Evaluation

          •Validation



          1. Preliminary development:

          In preliminary development, by referring to many articles,

          a mixture of multiple components such as starch, cellulose,

          waitrose, lyles, colouring dyes, albumin, etc, which were

          already present in existing alternatives, was developed in

          different ratios. Upon multiple attempts, the combination

          of albumin serum bovine, cellulose starch, and gram’s safr-
          anin  worked  out well.  Further,  numerous  substitutes  with

          these three components in different ratios were developed.

          Six  standard  substitutes  were  formulated  with  different

          compositions. Each of them was tested at least 20 times

          to ascertain the nature of blood formed in a perpendicular

          drop and angled drop.  The results with substitute no. 6

          showed promise as the nature of drop in both perpendic-
          ular and angled drops were found to be similar to that of

          blood. This substitute 6 was regarded as the best suitable

          substitute for the study and the test was replicated.




          2. Evaluation:

          For evaluation, the chosen substitute was tested repeatedly



                                                             63]]></page><page Index="65"><![CDATA[For evaluation, the chosen substitute was tested repeated-

                 ly several times against blood patterns for the correctness.

                 The procedure was, each time, the blood and substitute

                 comparison has been performed in 4 different patterns.
                 •  The perpendicular falls at 2 different heights one at 40

                    cm and the other at 70 cm height.

                 •  The  angled  fall  from  2  different  angles,  i.e.,  20  degrees

                    and 60 degrees

                 The comparison was done in the span of three days.

                 On Day 1: 8 trials were performed with both blood and

                 substitute
                 On Day 2: 40 repeats were done with 1 drop of blood

                 against 40 drops of substitute.

                 And on the final day, 15 repeats were performed with 15

                 drops of substitute against 1 drop blood









                 Fig no.1.Day 1- Drop 1 from       Fig no.2. Day 1- Drop 2 from
                 40cm height                                 70cm height

                 Fig no.3.Day 1- Drop 3 from       Fig no.4. Day 1- Drop 4 from

                 40cm height                                 70cm height


















                 Fig no.5. Day 1- Drop 1 from       Fig no.6. Day 1- Drop 2
                 from 20ᵒ angle                                      60ᵒ angle

                 Fig no.7. Day 1- Drop 1 from       Fig no.8. Day 1- Drop 2

                 from 20ᵒ angle                                      60ᵒ angle




                                                             64]]></page><page Index="66"><![CDATA[Fig no. 9. Day 2- 40 drops              Fig no. 10. Day 2- 40drops

                       from 40cm height                            from 70cm height




















                  Fig no. 11. Day 2- 40 drops           Fig no. 12. Day 2- 40drops
                          from 20ᵒ angle                               from 60ᵒ angle



























                     Fig no. 13. Day 3- 15 drops            Fig no. 14. Day 3- 15
                      from 40cm height                      drops  from 70cm height








                                                              65]]></page><page Index="67"><![CDATA[Fig no. 15. Day 3- 15 drops         Fig no. 16. Day 3- 15 drops

                       from 20degree angle                             from 60degree angle
                3. Validation:

                Under validation, the length and width of each drop were

                measured and noted for all the trials and compared with

                blood drops. The mean diameter for perpendicular drops

                was calculated and the mean width by length ratio and

                mean estimated angles were calculated for angled drops.
                The  average  of  different  attempts,  different  heights  and

                angles.  And  also,  deviation  between  the  values  was  also

                observed and calculated.





































                                 Table 1. Validation of perpendicular drops



                                                            66]]></page><page Index="68"><![CDATA[Validation of 20 degree drops












































           Table 2. Validation of 20 degree angled drops



           Validation of 60 degree drops





























           Table 3. Validation of 60degree angled drops








                                                             67]]></page><page Index="69"><![CDATA[RESULTS AND ANALYSIS

                 The above results and tables reveal the average of values

                 in each parameter chosen with respect to blood and the

                 substitute. In perpendicular drops of 20 cm and 70 cm
                 height, the study reveals that both with blood and sub-

                 stitute the diameter is more or less the same with a neg-

                 ligible standard deviation. In angled drops of 20 degree

                 angle, the study reveals that the width/length ratio has

                 more or less the same value for both blood and substi-

                 tute, but the estimated angle has a wide variation.  This

                 can be due to the crude means used to arrive at an angle
                 of 20 degree during the performance of the test. Similarly,

                 in angled drops of 60 degree angle, the study reveals that

                 the width/length ratio has more or less the same value for

                 both blood and substitute, but the estimated angle has a

                 wide variation. This can be due to the crude means used

                 to arrive at an angle of 60 degree during the performance

                 of the test.


                 CONCLUSION

                 In this study, the relation between the height of fall and

                 the shape of the drop as well as the angle of fall and the

                 size of the drop was demonstrated and established. The

                 diameter of the drop increased with the increase in height

                 and the tailing of the drop increased with the decrease in
                 the length.  Based  on the results  and validation of find-

                 ings, it can be concluded that the fictitious blood devel-

                 oped here can be employed as a preliminary working

                 alternative for additional research and academic studies

                 especially for demonstration and understanding of blood

                 pattern analysis with further development and standard-
                 ization. It was manufactured in a few products which



                                                             68]]></page><page Index="70"><![CDATA[were inexpensive and readily available and it could be

          prepared by anyone with no special equipment. It can

          also be stored and not harmful.




          REFERENCES:

          •  Attinger, D., Moore, C., Donaldson, A., Jafari, A., &
             Stone, H. A. (2013). Fluid dynamics topics in blood-

             stain pattern analysis: Comparative review and re-

             search opportunities. Forensic Science International,

             231(1–3),           375–396.            https://doi.org/10.1016/j.forsci-

             int.2013.04.018

          •  Banerjee, M. (1867). Basics of DNA Structure & Func-

             tion. University of Lucknow. lkouniv.ac.in
          •  Bharadwaj, P. (2016). Analysis of blood samples in

             Forensics. Research Gate. https://doi.org/10.13140/

             RG.2.2.28185.42088

          •  Divakar, K. P. (2017).  Forensic Odontology:  The New

             Dimension  in  Dental  Analysis. International  Journal  of
             Biomedical Science, 13(1), 1–4. www.ijbs.org

          •  Fakia, B. (2018).  The Branches of forensic botany. In-

             ternational Journal of Developmental Research,  Vol

             8(10), 23294–23297. http://www.journalijdr.com

          •  James, S. H.,  Kish,  P. E.,  & Sutton,  T. P.  (2002). Blood-

             stain Patterns. Introduction to Scientific and Investiga-

             tive Techniques, 4(1), 67–91. www.swgstain.org/
          •  Kenniscentrum  Voor De Gezondheidszorg, F. (2007).

             Laboratory tests in general practice. KCE Reports 59C.

             http://www.kce.fgov.be

          •  Lee, S.  Y., Seo,  Y. il, Moon, B. S., Kim, J. P., Goh, J. M.,

             Park, N. K., & Shin, S. H. (2020). Study on develop-

             ment of forensic blood substitute: Focusing on blood-

             stain pattern analysis. Forensic Science International,


                                                            69]]></page><page Index="71"><![CDATA[316. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.forsciint.2020.110461

                •  Mashaly, A., & Ibrahim, A. (2022). Forensic entomolo-

                   gy  research  in  Egypt:  a  review  article.  Egyptian  Journal

                   of Forensic Sciences, 12(1), 2–6. https://doi.org/10.1186/

                   s41935-022-00272-8

                •  Nishant, K.,  Vrijesh, K.  Y., & Ajay, K. R. (2017).  Wild-
                   life Forensic: Current  Techniques and their Limitations.

                   Journal of Forensic Science & Criminology, 5(3), 306.

                   https://www.researchgate.net/publication/319136233

                •  Rod Englert, K. P. (2010). Blood secrets. Chronicles of a

                   Crime Scene. scribd.com

                •  Sajid Mohammed, Z. (2016). Blood. Research Gate,

                   Chapter 1, 1–5. https://www.researchgate.net/publica-
                   tion/331993004

                •  Sarvesvaran, R. (1986). Blood as an Important tool

                   in  Crime  Investigation.  Acta  Medicinae  Legalis  et So-

                   cialis,       36(1),        262–264.           https://doi.org/10.19080/jfs-

                   ci.2017.03.555615
                •  Sharma, S., & Rohatgi, S. (2019). Forensic Existence

                   of Blood as a Dynamic Evidence. International Journal

                   of  Trend in Scientific Research and Development, 3(2),

                   467–471. www.ijtsrd.com

                •  Singh, P., Gupta, N., & Rathi, R. (2021). Blood pattern

                   analysis—a review and new findings. Egyptian Journal

                   of Forensic Sciences, 11(1), 2–7. https://doi.org/10.1186/
                   s41935-021-00224-8

                •  Stotesbury,  T., Illes, M.,  Wilson, P., &  Vreugdenhil, A.

                   J. (2017).  The application of silicon sol–gel technolo-

                   gy to forensic blood substitute development: Investiga-

                   tion of the spreading dynamics onto a paper surface. Fo-

                   rensic Science International, 275, 308–313. https://doi.

                   org/10.1016/j.forsciint.2017.03.020


                                                             70]]></page><page Index="72"><![CDATA[•  Vij, K.  (2011).  Textbook  of  Forensic Medicine and

             Toxicology. Elsevier, 5th edition, chapter 1-chapter 6.

             https://doi.org/10.1016/C2011-0-05147-5





























             FACTS !





           Teeth  are  typically  the  most  reliable

           identifiers when it comes to identifying

           a corpse. Teeth are bones, and bones last

           a long time so that’s why teeth are typi-

           cally used to identify bodies — they are
           correct around 93% of the time.
































                                                             71]]></page><page Index="73"><![CDATA[A PICTORIAL REPRESENTATION


                         OF THE ROLES OF A CRIME



                                         SCENE EXPERT




                                      Artwork by Nishani Sahoo





      INTRODUCTION




      Crime scene is the only place
      we  know for  certain  that  the

      accused and victim were in

      direct proximity with each

      other. It is a rich source of

      physical  evidences related to

      the crime and proper investi-
      gation of the crime scene can

      be of great benefit to the in-

      vestigation of the crime.



      Step 1

      Check on victims. Provide

      medical assistance if neces-

      sary.



      Step 2

      Secure and Protect the Scene.

      The crime scene should be

      properly barricaded and pro-
      tected from unauthorized

      personnel. Usually, the radio

      dispatch message is brief and

      seldom reveals the full nature

      of the incident.

                                                             72]]></page><page Index="74"><![CDATA[Step 3

                                                                Document  the  scene  –  Pho-

                                                                tography is a essential part of

                                                                scene documentation.











         Step 4

         Survey the scene and evaluate

         evidences and prepare a nar-

         rative and list of evidences to
         be collected.













                                                                Step 5

                                                                Collect evidences individu-

                                                                ally, following the collection

                                                                protocol for each of them.








        CONCLUSION




        As pointed out earlier, the crime
        scene is a very important entity in

        crime investigation. It is of prima-

        ry importance in all crimes.

        Picture with the finger clicking the

        centre of the smart art to be insert-

        ed here



                                                             73]]></page><page Index="75"><![CDATA[GLOBAL NEWS UPDATES



                                             RELATED TO



                                    FORENSIC SCIENCE













                 •  Forensic proteomics

                 •  Virtopsy







































                                                             74]]></page><page Index="76"><![CDATA[FORENSIC PROTEOMICS












            Ms. Kavya Priya.L




        Proteins are naturally occurring highly complex substances

        that consist of amino acid residues joined by a peptide bond.
        Protein is the major component of all biological evidence,

        where it can be used to identify body fluids and tissues, as

        well as convey genetic information in the form of single ami-

        no acid polymorphism. Proteomics is the study of proteomes

        (i.e, the total proteins of a given sample such as cultured

        cells, tissues, or an organism). It is a powerful approach to

        studying biological systems.
        Compared with immunological methods, proteomics may

        reduce time and overall costs. Forensic Proteomics directly

        analyzes proteins in blood cells, clothing fibers, medication,

        etc, for the applications like microbial characterization, pro-

        tein toxin detection, and forensic fluid analysis.




        PROTEOMICS METHODS
        Proteomics methods can be separated into top-down, mid-

        dle-down, and bottom-up approaches.

        In top-down proteomics, intact proteins are extracted from

        samples that are directly separated and analyzed by LC-MS/

        MS (Liquid Chromatography-Mass Spectrometry).  This ap-

        proach is widely used in sports anti-doping to identify banned

        proteins or peptides. In the bottom-up approach, proteins
        are digested into thousands of peptides such as trypsin and

        LysC.  In the  middle-down  approach,  protein  digestion is

        carried out but the real aim is to yield large peptides. The




                                                             75]]></page><page Index="77"><![CDATA[bottom-up method is the most used method of the three ap-

               proaches. The steps of the approach are shown here:




               i. Sample preparation:  includes sample pre-treatment, pro-

               tein extraction, proteolytic digestion, and peptide purifica-

               tion
               •  Sampling and sample pre-treatment: Samples can be col-

                   lected from human bodies (if there is) and crime scenes. The

                   techniques include wipes, dry swabs, aspirating needles,

                   air vacuums, and filters. After collection, for short-term

                   storage and -20 degree or -80 degree celsius for long-term

                   storage.  Pre-treatment  methods  are  selected  depending

                   on the sample type, if the sample-containing proteins are
                   exosomes, serum, plasma saliva, etc they don’t require ly-

                   sis pre-treatment, instead an amount of buffer is added to

                   favor enzymatic digestion steps. If the samples are cells, a

                   lysis step is applied to break the cell membrane.

               •  Protein extraction: They are extracted by simultaneous re-

                   moval of contaminants. Protein precipitation is the com-
                   mon method in which proteins are precipitated by organic

                   solvents and their mixtures with acids or sodium deoxy-

                   cholate. After precipitation, the protein pellets are collect-

                   ed and washed with pre-chilled acetone ahead of proteo-

                   lytic digestion.

               •  Proteolytic digestion: Methods that are widely used are in-
                   gel,  in-solution,  on-  bead,  and  filter-aided sample  prepa-

                   ration (FASP). In in-solution digestion, protein pellets are

                   mixed with 8M urea, which can increase protein stabili-

                   ty and denature protein structures, these are reduced and

                   then alkylated. Then proteins are digested with enzymes.

                   The resultant peptides have the preferred size for MS Se-

                   quencing.




                                                             76]]></page><page Index="78"><![CDATA[•  Peptide purification: pellet-purification is conducted using

            reversed-phase solid-phase extraction (SPE).  The eluted

            peptide from the extraction is subjected to lyophilization

            or vacuum drying.
        •  Sample  fractionation:  It  is  the  rare  step  that  can  reduce

            the complexity of pellets before LC-MS/MS Analysis. It is

            a 3D fractionation required to achieve a proteome profile.




        ii. Data acquisition: Depending on data acquisition types,

        there is targeted and untargeted proteomics, where the un-

        targeted aims to collect data in large numbers and is used to
        profile the proteome of the sample, the targeted only detects

        and quantifies a small number of peptides. It is carried out

        in a triple-quadrupole mass spectrometer.




        iii. Data analysis: Database search is one method where the

        theoretical spectra are generated from peptide sequences via

        silico-digestion.  Another approach is MS/MS spectra library
        search.  The next method is de novo peptide identification,

        which uses spectra to determine sequences without databas-

        es.



























                       Figure: Processes of the bottom-up approach
                   ( https://images.app.goo.gl/U1WizdGSR5sJ2XCh7 )





                                                             77]]></page><page Index="79"><![CDATA[APPLICATIONS OF FORENSIC PROTEOMICS

               •  Hair proteome:  Human hair proteins are extracted by

                   the shotgun-proteomics approach, which demonstrates a
                   large extractability and variety of hair proteins after de-

                   tergent extraction.

               •  Bone proteome:  This can be used to study biomarkers

                   and therapeutic procedures in osteoporosis, bone mar-

                   row aging linked to genetic changes in the proteome, and

                   also about bone cancer.

               •  Organ identification:  The study found highly discrimi-
                   nating proteins in different organs. The proteomics anal-

                   ysis of the tissue can be further investigated for future

                   applications.

               •  Brain and cerebrospinal  fluid (CSF): CSF is used to de-

                   termine the time of death by comparing the proteome

                   profiles of antemortem and postmortem CSF, which is

                   performed by 2D gel electrophoresis and MS.



               REFERENCES:

               1. Van-an Duong, Park,2021, Proteomics in forensic anal-

                   ysis,       Retrieved           from         https://www.mdpi.com/2076-

                   3417/11/8/3393
               2. Rebekah Orton, 2020, Retrieved from https://www.pnnl-

                   gov/news-media/forensic-proteomics-beyond-dna-profil-

                   ing#:~:text=Forensic%20                     proteomics%20                 directly%20

                   analysis%20                proteins,detection%2C%20and%20foren-

                   sic%20fluid%20analysis.

               3. Glendon parker, Legg, Goecker, 2021, Retrieved from

                   https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34139528/












                                                             78]]></page><page Index="80"><![CDATA[VIRTOPSY












           Ms. Nishani Sahoo




        Virtopsy is a term extracted from two words  “virtual” and

        “autopsy.” It employs imaging methods that are routine-

        ly used in clinical medicine, such as computed tomography
        and magnetic resonance imaging in the field of the autopsy,

        to find the reason for death.

        Virtopsy is a multi-disciplinary technology that combines fo-

        rensic medicine and pathology, roentgenology (radiology),

        computer graphics, biomechanics, and physics.  The branch

        of forensics has made exemplary and path-breaking con-

        tributions to help solve these problems.  This approach has
        been recently used by forensic odontologists but has yet to

        make its own mark in the field.




        AUTOPSY V/S VIRTOPSY

        Conventional autopsy involves invasive procedures that are

        the traditional means of post-mortem examination in hu-

        mans. Contrary to it, virtopsy is a minimally invasive emerg-
        ing technology in the field of forensic medicine that incor-

        porates imaging technology of radiologists and forensic

        clinicians to reflect an ethical face in forensic examination.




        AIIMS (All India Institute Of Medical Science) and ICMR

        (Indian  Council of  Medical  Research)  are working together

        on a technique for post-mortem without incising/ dissecting
        the body. This technique is likely to become functional in a

        few months. Health Minister Harsh  Vardhan highlighted to

        Rajya Sabha that it is likely to be possible soon to carry out


                                                            79]]></page><page Index="81"><![CDATA[autopsies without dissecting the body.




               HISTORY

                S. No        Name of                      Credit                                  Year

                             scientists

                1.           Erasistratus and  Dissected on dead bod- 1700

                             Herophilus                   ies to study organs and

                                                          nerves

                2.           Giovanni                     Published            book         on 1761

                             Morgagni                     “The seats and causes

                                                          of disease”

                3.           William Osler                Taught autopsy as part  1800

                                                          of medical education

                4.           Wilhelm                      Initiated the first X-rays  1895

                             Rontgen                      experiment

                5.           Group           project Conducted the first body  1999

                             (unknown)                    scan for a high-profile

                                                          case through project

                                                          names like  “digital au-

                                                          topsy”  or “scalpel-free

                                                          autopsy”



               EQUIPMENT FOR AUTOPSY

               Virtopsy utilizes powerful scanning and radiographic tech-

               nology with the power and resolution of modern comput-

               ers. Virtopsy includes the following tools:

               •  3D surface scan using a 3D photogrammetry-based opti-

                   cal surface scanner
               •  Post-mortem Computed  Tomography (PMCT) with ad-

                   juvants such as PMCT-guided biopsy

               •  Post-mortem MRI (Magnetic Resonance Imaging)




                                                             80]]></page><page Index="82"><![CDATA[PROCEDURE

         1. Prepare the corpse for imaging.

         2. Place small disks along the body’s exterior so that the

            surface scan and the interior scans can easily be aligned.

            These disks mark points that can be used for rendering the
            images into a single cohesive image.

         3. Use virtibot to avoid inaccuracies while placing the mark-

            ers on the surface of the body.

         4. The markers are used to calibrate the exterior scan of the

            corpse and match it with internal imaging processes.

         5. A 3D color model of the corpse is accomplished.
         6. 0.02 mm resolution stereoscopic cameras are used to cap-

            ture the color image.

         7. The body is brought to the CT and MRI workplace, usual-

            ly double-covered inside a blue bag through which X-rays

            can easily pass, and then the body is laid on the sliding ta-

            ble of the CT, MRI, and MRS (Magnetic Resonance Spec-

            troscopy) equipment.
         8. A pathologist has the freedom to peel through the layers

            of virtual skin and muscle with the click of a computer

            mouse.

         9. Internal and surface scans and a needle biopsy can be done

            if internal body samples are needed.




         ADVANTAGES OF VIRTOPSY
         •  3D illustration

         •  Easy accessibility

         •  Allows for a digital re-examination of the body after the

            liberation of the crime scene and burial or rot of the corpse

            even decades later

         •  Less time-consuming, aids in better diagnosis, and renders

            respect to religious sentiments, and


                                                            81]]></page><page Index="83"><![CDATA[•  Can be used for telemedicine/teleforensic/telepathology


























               https://www.researchgate.net/figure/Virtopsy-equipment-From-

               left-to-right-camera-surface-scanner-biopsy-tool-and-CT-scanner_

                                                     fig1_329444591



               FIRST VIRTUAL AUTOPSY IN SAUDI ARABIA

               Case description
               The deceased was a female stillbirth. A virtual autopsy was

               conducted to determine the cause of death. The post-mor-

               tem scan was performed by a

               •  General Electrical (GE) lightspeed 16 multi-detector com-

                   puterized tomography scan

               •  The PMCT speciﬁcations were 180 mAs, 120 kVp, and a

                   measured FOV (Field of View) of 50 cm.
               •  This was reconstructed to images of 0.625 mm slice thick-

                   ness at 1.375:1 pitch.




               Observation

               •  The CT images revealed signiﬁcant enlargement of both

                   kidneys with numerous bilateral cystic hypodense lesions,-

                   mainly in peripheral areas, causing destruction of the nor-
                   mal renal parenchyma.

               •  The renal pelvis was under-developed, and mild ﬂank dis-

                   tention was observed.


                                                             82]]></page><page Index="84"><![CDATA[•  Following this, a forensic pathologist, using standard dis-

              section and tissue analysis, conducted a manual autopsy

              with a biopsy of kidney tissue for laboratory analysis.

              The diagnosis was multicystic dysplastic kidney disease
              (MCDK), as there was evidence of renal dysplasia.




          CONCLUSION

          The procedure shows a relatively good degree of accuracy,

          but it may fail to stand on its own without the aid of min-

          imally invasive procedures (biopsies). However, the degree

          of invasiveness is small and therefore still acceptable under
          cultural limitations.
























          Coronal mid-abdomen cross-sec-                    gross kidney structure with bi-

          tional CT  image showing enlarge-                lateral presentation showing dys-
          ment of both kidneys  with diffuse                              plastic ducts.

                         hypodensity.

          https://w w w.researchgate.net/figure/Images-show-

          ing-the-a-gross-kidney-structure-with-bilateral-presenta-
                                     tion-and-b-a_fig2_268690557




          REFERENCE:
          •  Aljerian, K. and Alqahtani, S., 2014. First virtual autop-

              sy in Saudi Arabia: A case report with literature review.

              researchgate. Retrieved from https://www.researchgate.




                                                            83]]></page><page Index="85"><![CDATA[net/publication/268690557_First_virtual_autopsy_in_

                  Saudi
               •  Tsui,  H.  C.  L.  (2020).  Virtopsy  as  a  Revolutionary  Tool

                   for Cetacean Stranding Programs: Implementation and

                   Management. Frontiers. Retrieved from https://www.

                   frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fmars.2020.542015/full

               •  n.d.  Virtopsy – Forensic Medicine, University of Zurich.

                   Retrieved from https://virtopsy.com/

























                                            DID YOU KNOW?





                                            Which forensic unit studies handwrit-

                                            ing and typewriting on questioned docu-

                                            ments, also analysing paper or ink?



                                            Answer: Questioned Documents Unit

























                                                             84]]></page><page Index="86"><![CDATA[The first graduating batch (UG batch of 2019-22) of the

               Department of Forensic Science, Kristu Jayanti College, Bangalore










































                     Department of Forensic Science at Kristu Jayanti College,

              Bangalore initiated the MSc Forensic Science programme from the
                                            academic year 2022-23.




                                                             85]]></page><page Index="87"><![CDATA[-































                                       CASE STUDIES















                    •  Pegasus

                    •  The grim sleeper serial killer

                    •  The unabomber or the psycho genius?

                    •  Gauri lankesh assassination








































                                                               86]]></page><page Index="88"><![CDATA[PEGASUS










          Ms. Merien Abraham



          Pegasus is the spying software built by the Israeli NSO (Niv,

          Shalev and Omri, names of the company’s founders) group

          (the cyber agency that deals with all the cyber problems

          straight from the central or federal government) to spy on
          the digital groups to keep a check on the terrorist and all

          those  criminals  who  are  harmful  to  their  country.  It  has

          been named after the horse in Greek Mythology, Pegasus

          which  looks  like  a unicorn.  It  was  used to  get  all  the doc-

          uments,  information and  small to  small things  from your

          phone, even the ongoing conversation with just this soft-

          ware without the help of any human intervention or help.




























                             https://www.kaspersky.com/blog/




          At that  time  whoever were  residing  in Israel were told to

          put this software on their devices so that they can keep a
          check on those people and whoever used to go against its

          use to declare them as terrorist or a threat to the country.





                                                             87]]></page><page Index="89"><![CDATA[But later stages a news came out from the media that Pega-

                sus was being given to the US officials but then later it was

                again taken back. Earlier through apps, they used to install

                it but nowadays with just messages, it will get installed on
                your phone without your notice.

                But after all this incident a complaint was filed from the US,

                that some of their officials’ devices were hacked and many

                other neighboring countries also complained that even Isra-

                el used this software to spy on their enemy countries by get-

                ting  their  personal  or  secret  information. Many other com-

                plaints were filed from other countries  and even famous
                companies like Facebook, iOS, Blackberry, and WhatsApp.




                There were around 121 attempts done but still, 20 were

                successful according to the report given by WhatsApp. They

                even said that it was really difficult to find out what was the

                information taken by the attacker and how much, it’s just

                that they used to send some messages before attacking. And
                usually, the victims who are targeted will be an activist or

                the politicians or leaders or journalists, or any known per-

                son.




                Now if we come to how Pegasus affected India, it targeted
                mainly the Politician and the socialists especially. E.g., Ra-

                hul Gandhi, Prashant Kishor, Alok  Verma, Umar Khalid,

                etc.  Many  complaints  were  put  down  by  other  common

                people also who got targeted by Pegasus to

                CERT-In (Indian Computer Emergency Response  Team) to

                look after this thing seriously. According to media and the

                journal reports, they said that this matter is very serious
                and needs to be dealt with as soon as possible as the soft-

                ware which is attacking the devices is been dealt with by



                                                             88]]></page><page Index="90"><![CDATA[the people who don’t have any relation with our country

         and have no authority to be dealing with the information of

         ours and even the peeping into someone else’s private mat-

         ters is practically illegal.




         But because of this many illegal things and crimes done by

         these higher officials were caught red handed so the case was
         denied by the central government. There are still no proper

         actions taken from any government against it as it is still

         run by NSO even though in some interviews they said that

         now they don’t have any direct connection with Pegasus.




         The only way to be secured from all these spying software
         is to not allow or accept any foreign or unknown or fraud

         messages. Always keep an anti-virus software app on your

         phone or computer and regularly do the proper cleaning

         (internal) of the devices. If any unnatural act you feel is hap-

         pening on your device immediately complain to the police.



         “One single vulnerability is all an attacker needs”




                                                                 Quote by -Window Snyder

                                                              Chief Security Officer, Fastly



         REFERENCES

         •  Gurijala B. (August 9, 2021).  What is Pegasus? A cyber-
             security expert explains how the spyware invades phones

             and what it does when it gets in. Morgantown, West Vir-

             ginia. https://theconversation.com/what-is-pegasus-a-cy-

             bersecurity-expert-explains-how-the-spyware-invades-

             phones-and-what-it-does-when-it-gets-in-165382

         •  TIMES OF INDIA. (Jul 18, 2021). Pegasus spyware used



                                                             89]]></page><page Index="91"><![CDATA[http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/articleshow/84531126

                   .cms?utm_source=contentofinterest&utm_medium=tex

                   t&utm_campaign=cppst

                •  Mazoomdaar J. (August 13, 202). How Pegasus spyware

                    infects  a  device;  what  data  may  be  compromised.  New

                    Delhi, India. https://indianexpress.com/article/explained/
                    pegasus-whatsapp-spyware-israel-india-7410890/






























                                            MYTH BUSTERS





                                            Myth: Advanced DNA testing gives im-

                                            mediate results of  a suspect or an indi-
                                            vidual.

                                            Fact:  DNA analysis takes several hours

                                            to give results. In a typical laboratory

                                            scenario it takes more than 30 days.





















                                                            90]]></page><page Index="92"><![CDATA[THE GRIM SLEEPER



                                          SERIAL KILLER











            Ms. Anumita Mazumdar





          Overview:

          Lonnie David Franklin Jr, also given the nickname the
          Grim Sleeper, was held liable for more than 10 murders

          committed  in  California.  It  is  believed  that  his  killing

          spree was between the mid-80s till 2007. Due to large

          durations of time between his murders and underutilized

          DNA evidence found from the scene of the crime, it was

          nearly  impossible  to hunt  down a  suspect.  Franklin was

          finally  arrested  in  the  year  2010  after  forensic  scientists
          used familial DNA searching to link the DNA evidence

          found at the crime scene to that of Franklin’s relative.

          Through  the  following  questions,  we  will  try  to  under-

          stand this case in detail!





























          https://www.rollingstone.com/culture/culture-features/grim-

               sleeper-serial-killer-everything-you-need-to-know-252246/



                                                            91]]></page><page Index="93"><![CDATA[Why was he the terror of L.A?

                 Though he was held responsible for more than 10 mur-

                 ders, it is believed that he has murdered more than 25

                 women. After exactly 6 years, and three and a half months

                 of trial he was sentenced to death on August 10th, 2016.

                 His first victim was named Debra Jackson whom he shot
                 3 times in the chest with a .25 caliber gun. He used to

                 take pictures of his victims and keep them in his home as

                 souvenirs.  There are various doubts raised as to why it

                 took so long for LAPD (Los Angeles Police Department)

                 to catch this man. Many had the theory that it went un-

                 noticed with the fact that most of his victims were black

                 women prostitutes and drug-addicted women.



                 What do we know about him?

                 Franklin was a sanitation worker and had access to var-

                 ious landfills and waste dumping grounds. During the

                 investigation, several questions were asked to Franklin’s

                 neighbor, as to what he was like in person. Most of them

                 said that he was  “friendly and quiet”. He used to talk
                 to everyone and was quite social which does not fit the

                 description of a serial killer. His murders were going un-

                 noticed because at that time the use of drugs and related

                 crimes were common in L.A. In addition to this, due to

                 the racial discrimination practiced in America, most of

                 these black women murders were being ignored. As a re-

                 sult, an association called the Black Coalition Fighting
                 Back Serial Murders (1989) was formed.  The main pur-

                 pose  of  forming  this  association  was  to  raise  awareness

                 about  these murders  taking place and to protect  black

                 women in South and Central L.A.





                                                             92]]></page><page Index="94"><![CDATA[A not-so-simple question - How was he caught?

          It is well known that no crime is perfect. Something is

          always left behind and if the investigation is carried out

          swiftly and strictly, it will be a lot easier to catch the per-
          petrator.  Enietra  Washington, the  only survivor of  these

          killings, testified against him. Her bullet wounds were

          matched with the previously collected evidence. Enietra

          was shot and raped in 1988. She went on to explain how

          he asked her to get into his car when she denied he shot

          her because she was being disrespectful.

          Familial DNA testing was enough for Franklin to be
          charged with murder.  The collected DNA evidence was

          matched with his relative’s DNA present in the system, a

          person called Christopher (his son) who was arrested for

          felony weapons possession in 2009. Soon after obtaining

          the DNA, undercover cops  followed him to  a birthday

          party being held in L.A. They collected the plates and piz-

          za leftovers which had enough DNA to land him behind
          the bars.




          A shocking discovery!

          After a thorough search of his house, investigators found

          nearly more than 1000 photos of black women and ado-

          lescent girls. Some of them were unconscious, naked while

          many were bleeding and seemed to be dead. At this dis-
          covery, the  police wondered  if there were more victims

          than they initially thought…



          REFERENCES:

          •  Zuppello,S. (2016).  ‘Grim Sleeper’ Serial Killer: Every-
              thing You Need to Know. Rolling Stone. Retrieved from

              https://www.rollingstone.com/culture/culture-features/



                                                             93]]></page><page Index="95"><![CDATA[grim-sleeper-serial-killer-everything-you-need-to-

                   know-252246/

                •  Just Science. (2020). JUST  THE GRIM SLEEPER

                    SERIAL KILLER. Forensic  Technology Center of

                    Excellence. Retrieved from https://forensiccoe.org/
                    casestudies-episode5/















































                                            DID YOU KNOW?




                                            Even if you move a file to the trash on

                                            your computer, it remains in a hidden file

                                            that a digital forensic investigator can

                                            find.












                                                             94]]></page><page Index="96"><![CDATA[THE UNABOMBER OR THE



                                     PSYCHO GENIUS?








            Ms. Siddhi Pant



         The famed wound collector or the Unabomber Ted Kaczyns-

         ki is responsible for the gathering of mail bombings, killing

         3 people. son to Polish-Americans  Theodore and  Wanda

         Kaczynski.  He  modified  right  into  a  prodigy,  excelling  at

         mathematics at an early age. Funding himself with uncom-
         mon jobs and economic help from his family, Kaczynski

         studied survival skills collectively with match-to-be-eaten

         plant identification, tracking, and primitive construction.

























         https://tse1.mm.bing.net/th?id=OIP.kClr87WxiTFb3Jw5EYod-
                             kQHaEK&pid=Api&P=0&w=274&h=154




         The math prodigy becomes the Unabomber

         Between 1978 and 1995, the Unabomber terrorized the

         mail with domestically made bombs that killed three people
         and injured 23 others. Each device the Unabomber sent out

         was uniquely made. Many of the devices had been made

         of, or with, timber. In most cases, the explosives had been



                                                             95]]></page><page Index="97"><![CDATA[made from gunpowder, match heads, and other common

                available items. One resembled a cigar box and was left

                in a North-western University, now no longer an unusual

                place. Another, disguised as a wooden board with protrud-
                ing nails, appeared withinside the front of a computer shop.




                Industrial Society and Its Future

                Kaczynski’s 35,000-word essay called  “Industrial Society

                and Its Future” is a social critique opposing industrializa-

                tion and a herbal ode to nature-focused anarchism.  The

                essay contends that the Industrial Revolution commenced
                a harmful approach of natural destruction delivered upon

                through the manner of the era, whilst forcing human beings

                to comply with machinery, growing a socio-political order

                that suppresses human freedom and potential.
















                https://tse2.mm.bing.net/th?id=OIP.rCQhqNahxFdCLchGTEK-

                                   megHaC5&pid=Api&P=0&w=470&h=184




                Modus operandi

                Kaczynski’s bombs were handmade pipe bombs and typi-
                cally contained handcrafted additives of timber. Also, bits

                of  timber or  bark  had  been frequently  covered withinside

                the  constructions.  He  taught himself the manner  to  make

                the explosives out of quantities of scrap material and


                                                            96]]></page><page Index="98"><![CDATA[timber that were modified into untraceable materials. The

         construction was completed manually, without the assis-

         tance of power systems to make the smooth system he

         needed.





















         https://tse4.mm.bing.net/th?id=OIP.8_biQW7N1jGnZFKc1lF3-A

                               HaD7&pid=Api&P=0&w=306&h=162



         The surge to save humanity

         Kaczynski stated he went after figureheads, massive and

         small, of the digital revolution as a fashion of  “revenge”

         and approach to stop humanity from itself. Kaczynski’s
         first victim on May 25, 1978, modified into  Terry Marker,

         a police officer on-responsibility at North-western Univer-

         sity.

         On November 15, 1979, he located a bomb within the car-

         go of American Airlines Flight 444.  The bomb caused  “a

         sucking explosion and a loss of pressure”.

         On June 10, 1980, a parcel was modified and sent to the res-
         idence of United Airlines president Percy Wood. The bomb

         was rigged withinside the book “Ice Brothers” through the

         manner of the way of Sloan  Wilson. He suffered from es-

         sential burns and cuts all over his body.


         Forensic linguistic: The breakthrough

         Forensic Linguistics provides a careful and systemic



                                                             97]]></page><page Index="99"><![CDATA[assessment of language. The Unabomber’s writing style was

                examined through his family members, who, after investi-
                gating on their end, sadly determined that their findings had

                to be reported. Ted’s brother, David, found out his brother

                was the Unabomber through the written words modified

                but needed to be reinforced through extra methods.  The

                linguistic assessment was done by FBI (Federal Bureau of

                Investigation) agents. FBI used a smooth computational
                approach looking at word frequencies and spelling versions

                to build up a linguistic profile to observe and match the au-

                thors. For example, similarities covered every author using

                “analyse”  for “analyze,” “licence”  for “license,” “wilful-

                ly” rather than  “willfully,”  “instalment” rather than  “in-

                stallment,” and so forth.
                The FBI profiler, James Fitzgerald, recognized a weird ver-

                sion of the idiom “you can’t have your cake and eat it too!”

                -  Kaczynski  and  the  Unabomber  inverted  it  into “you  can’t

                eat your cake and characteristic it too”.  There had been

                many exceptional similarities in content, style, and expres-

                sion between  Ted Kaczynski’s work and that of the Un-

                abomber’s manifesto.
























                         http://www.unabombers.com/images/MNight1.gif






                                                             98]]></page><page Index="100"><![CDATA[The end of the manhunt

          With the help of Ted’s brother, David, and the assessment

          performed by the FBI profiler, James Fitzgerald, using fo-

          rensic linguistics, the genius criminal was behind the bars

          for  the bombings.  As a  result,  the  wound  collector  plead-
          ed accountable for all the bombings. He was sentenced to

          eight terms with no parole.



          REFERENCES:

          •  Brogle,  C. (2020,  February 22).  Who  Were the  Victims

             of Unabomber  Ted Kaczynski’s Acts of  Terror? Oxygen

             Official Site. Retrieved from https://www.oxygen.com/

             true-crime-buzz/who-were-unabomber-ted-kaczynskis-

             victims

          •  Michelakis, P. (2022, January 3). Analysis of the Un-
             abomber’s Manifesto (Part 1) - ILLUMINATION. Me-

             dium. Retrieved from https://medium.com/illumination/

             analysis-of-the-unabombers-manifesto-part-1-27dfb-

             0fbdf8a

          •  Unabomber. (2022, April 5). Federal Bureau of Investi-

             gation. Retrieved from  https://www.fbi.gov/history/fa-

             mous-cases/unabomber
          •  Lou, C. (2018,  August 15).  Fighting  Words with the Un-

             abomber.  JSTOR  Daily.  Retrieved  from  https://daily.

             jstor.org/fighting-words-unabomber/

          •  Sanders, S. (2021, February 18).  This is how the Un-

             abomber was finally caught. Grunge.Com. Retrieved

             from  https://www.grunge.com/336863/this-is-how-the-
             unabomber-was-finally-caught/











                                                             99]]></page><page Index="101"><![CDATA[GAURI LANKESH



                                         ASSASINATION







                                                                           Ms. Neha Elsa John



























               https://www.indiatoday.in/india/story/gauri-lankesh-s-mur-
               der-was-planned-a-year-before-exclusive-details-of-the-kill-

                                             ing-1326868-2018-08-29




               “I will do what I can, and I will say what I should.  These

               intolerant voices find strength in our silence. Let them learn
               to argue using words instead of threats.”  ~ Gauri Lankesh




               Gauri Lankesh,  born in Karnataka on 29th January 1962,

               was  an  Indian  journalist  and  activist  who  was  the  editor

               of Lankesh Patrike. She started her journalism life in the

               Times of India. Gauri Lankesh was a fearless journalist

               who openly criticized the caste system and Hindu nation-
               alists.




               Assassination

               On 5th September 2017, Gauri Lankesh was shot dead in

               front of her residence in South Bangalore by two people who




                                                            100]]></page><page Index="102"><![CDATA[arrived on a motorcycle. The autopsy report revealed that

          three bullets pierced through her body. One of the bullets

          entered her body from behind her left shoulder, and the
          other two from the front damaged her lungs and heart. Po-

          lice revealed that they were able to find four cartridges and

          fragments of bullets, and the fourth bullet, which missed

          the target, was recovered from the wall. On November

          23rd, 2018, a charge sheet was prepared, and 18 persons

          were accused of her murder. Parashuram  Waghmare was
          the shooter, and others like Amol Kale, Amit Degwekar,

          and Sujith Kumar were the masterminds behind the crime.

          Once Parashuram Waghmare even confessed that he didn’t

          know who he was killing. He was told that he had to kill

          someone to save his religion. The statement given by Para-

          suram Waghmore was as follows:



          “I  was  told  in  May  2017  I  had  to  kill  someone  to  save  my

          religion. I agreed. I didn’t know who the victim was. Now

          I feel that I should not have killed the women.”




          He also said that he was brought to Bengaluru on Septem-

          ber 3 and made him practice shooting using an air gun.



          On examining the gun used to shoot Gauri Lankesh, the

          investigators were able to find out that the same gun was

          used to kill M.M. Kalburgi, who was a Kannada schol-

          ar, and Leftist thinker Govind Pansare, in the year 2015.

          The SIT (Special Investigation Team) has said in the charge

          sheet that the Hindu extremist organization, Sanatan Sans-

          tha, was responsible for the murder of Gauri Lankesh. The
          SIT also said that the murder of Gauri Lankesh was linked

          to the murders of other left-leaning activists and



                                                             101]]></page><page Index="103"><![CDATA[rationalists, Professor MM Kalburgi, Narendra Dabhol-

                kar, and Govind Pansare. The SIT had stated in court that

                Gauri Lankesh was targeted for opposing Hindutva vehe-

                mently in her writing and speeches.



                Other related cases:

                Narendra Dabholkar, M.M Kalburgi, Govind Pansare, and

                Gauri Lankesh were four activists who openly criticized

                caste systems and Hindutva politics.

                Narendra Achyut Dabholka, an Indian physician, activist,

                and author from Maharashtra, was shot to death on 20
                August 2013 while out on a morning walk. Malleshappa

                Madivalappa Kalburgi, an Indian scholar of  Vachana Sa-

                hitya (Vachana literature) in the Kannada language and

                academic who served as the vice-chancellor of Kannada

                University in Hampi, was shot to death on 30th August

                2015, by two men who came in a motorcycle in point-

                blank range striking his chest and forehead, and on 16th
                February 2015, the veteran communist leader, rationalist

                thinker, senior labor lawyer, and prolific writer Govind

                Pansare was shot at close range outside his house and was

                pronounced dead on 20th February.




                Some of the key findings from the Gauri Lankesh investi-

                gations have a bearing on the other cases as well:
                •  The murder of Lankesh outside her front door by two

                   men on a motorcycle shows a resemblance to the Au-

                   gust 30, 2015 murder of Kalburgi at the doorstep of his

                   home in Dharwad in north Karnataka.

                •  Nine day after the murder, the Karnataka Police SIT was
                   provided with a significant forensic finding: the 7.65 mm

                   country-made gun that was used to kill Lankesh was



                                                            102]]></page><page Index="104"><![CDATA[the same one that was used to shoot Kalburgi two years

             previously, said a ballistics report from the state forensic

             lab.

          •  The ballistic evidence from the Kalburgi case had already

             linked the Kannada scholar’s murder to those of Pansare,

             81, in Kolhapur, Maharashtra, on February 16, 2015,

             and Dabholkar, 67, in Pune on August 20, 2013, and the
             SIT concluded that one group or gang was involved in

             all the three murders. Investigations in Maharashtra by

             the  CBI (Central  Bureau of  Investigation) in  the Dabhol-

             kar case had revealed the involvement of members of the

             Sanatan Sanstha.






          REFERENCES:

          •  India  Today.  2022.  Narendra Dabholkar murder  case:

             CBI submits list of 32 witnesses. [online] Retrieved from

             https://www.indiatoday.in/india/story/narendra-dab-

             holkar-murder-case-cbi-submits-list-of-32-witness-

             es-1864535-2021-10-14.
          •  Staff,  T., 2022. Gauri Lankesh murder: Four years on,

             this is where the case stands. [online]  The News Min-

             ute. Retrieved from https://www.thenewsminute.com/

             article/gauri-lankesh-murder-four-years-where-case-

             stands-154850.

          •  NewsClick. 2022.  They Cannot  Silence Dabholkar, Pan-
             sare, Kalburgi, or Gauri Lankesh | NewsClick. [online].

             Retrieved from https://www.newsclick.in/they-cannot-

             silence-dabholkar-pansare-kalburgi-or-gauri-lankesh.












                                                            103]]></page><page Index="105"><![CDATA[FEATURE ARTICLES



















                   •  How pollen is a silent witness in crime

                   •  Forensic radiology in post-mortem

                   investigation


                   •  A new dimension in forensics





































                                                             104]]></page><page Index="106"><![CDATA[HOW POLLEN IS A SILENT


                                     WITNESS IN CRIME









          Ms. Supriya PV

          Ms. Aditi S Pai
          Ms. Natasha Jennifer Easu


          The pollen grain is not frequently encountered at a crime

          scene, but if encountered, it can lead to an investigation.

          Palynology is the study of pollen grains, spores, etc., while

          forensic palynology refers to the application of palynology

          to investigate civil and criminal cases.













          https://gapp.org/how-does-the-pollen-grain-develop/




          Pollen is a fine powder discharged from the male repro-

          ductive organ of a flower. The size of a pollen grain ranges
          from 10 to 150 micrometres (i.e., it cannot be seen with

          the naked eye) that is protected by a cell wall consisting of

          cellulose, pectin, and sporopollenin, making it resistant to

          decomposition. Pollen grains are transferred by wind, wa-

          ter, insects, butterflies, etc., for better propagation.

          They get attached to most surfaces and are deeply embedded

          in clothing. Hence, even washing clothes with detergents
          cannot remove all pollen grains attached.  The first case

          where the pollen was used to solve the case was in Austria

          in 1959. In this case, a man had gone missing, and the police

          arrested a suspect who had a motive to kill the man, but they



                                                            105]]></page><page Index="107"><![CDATA[had no evidence to prove so. On searching the suspect’s be-

                longings, they found a pair of muddy boots. The mud sam-

                ple was given to palynologist Wilhelm Klaus for analysis.
                The result showed that it contains a variety of species of

                pollen grain which can be found only near a small area

                around  Vienna.  When  these  findings  were briefed  to the

                suspect, he willingly confessed all about the murder and

                led authorities to the site of both murder and body, which

                were exactly in the area pinpointed by Dr. Klaus.

                Pollen collected from a person can match the scene of the
                crime, which suggests that the person might have visited

                that particular area recently, but it doesn’t mean they have

                committed the crime.

                Images of pollen grains can be obtained by three methods,

                namely:

                1. Transmitted-light microscopy (TLM),

                2. Widefield fluorescent method, and
                3. Structured illumination (Apotome) method.

                These methods are semi-automated traditional methods

                that are used to detect pollen grains.




                APPLICATIONS OF PALYNOLOGY

                Pollen  grain provides  a link  between  the victim, suspect,

                and crime scene. Pollen grains  can  help in  reconstructing
                the crime, understanding the modus operandi, and iden-

                tifying the molecular level using DNA (Deoxyribonucle-

                ic acid) typing. It can determine primary and secondary

                crime scenes. It will determine the movement history of

                materials,  including  drugs. It will give  information on  the
                geographic condition of the pollen grain.










                                                             106]]></page><page Index="108"><![CDATA[COLLECTION

         It is important to follow a simple method to collect pollen

         grains from clothes. The adhesive tape method is most suit-
         able for recovering pollen from clothes. It is simpler, faster,

         and less expensive than other methods.

         A pollen fingerprint is the number and type of pollen grains

         found in a geographic area at a specific time of the year.

         Low temperature decreases the rate of cell growth. Hence,

         pollen grains are preserved in liquid nitrogen at -196ᵒC. This

         is known as cryopreservation.



         EXAMINATION

         Structures of exine, the polar and equatorial shape, size, dis-

         persal form, and other morphology of pollen are examined,

         and conclusions are made.


























                       https://www.vcbio.science.ru.nl/en/virtuallessons/

                                            pollenmorphology/



         POLLEN PRESERVED AS FOSSILS

         The exine of a pollen grain is constituted by sporopollenin,

         which is found to be one of the most resistant organic ma-

         terials. Organic compounds such as long-chain fatty acids,

         phenylpropanoids, phenolics, and traces of carotenoids are




                                                          107]]></page><page Index="109"><![CDATA[chemically cross-linked to give sporopollenin its rigid struc-

                ture. This rigid structure can withstand high temperatures

                and strong alkalis and protect the pollen grain under harsh
                conditions.  This leads to resistance against microbial and

                chemical decomposition, which is why pollen grains are

                well preserved during fossilisation.

                With time, some pollen grains fall into lakes, where it gets

                accumulated with other sediments forming layers with

                each passing year. Due to a lack of oxygen (which is re-

                quired for decomposition) in the lake sediments, the pol-
                len grain remains as is. If the land remains wet, the pollen

                grains will perdure for millions of years.




                REFERENCES:

                •  Sawyer, A. (2020, September 3). How Can Forensic Paly-

                    nology Help Solve Crimes. Retrieved from https://www.

                    biotechniques.com/analytical-chemistry/a-silent-wit-
                    ness-how-analysis-of-pollen-can-solve-crimes/

                •  Alotaibi et al (2020). Pollen molecular biology: Appli-

                    cations in the forensic palynology and future prospects:

                    A review. Saudi Journal of Biological Sciences, 27(5),

                    1185–1190. Retrieved from https://doi.org/10.1016/j.

                    sjbs.2020.02.019





























                                                            108]]></page><page Index="110"><![CDATA[FORENSIC RADIOLOGY


                                       IN POST-MORTEM



                                          INVESTIGATION









         Ms. Rainelle R. Dennesen




          A post-mortem (autopsy) examination, carried out on the

          body of a deceased person - conducted in cases of suspi-

          cious/unnatural deaths or MLCs (Medico-Legal Cases), is

          performed by doctors specialized in Forensic Medicine. It

          is conducted systematically and aids in:

          •  Determining decedent’s identity

          •  Determining mechanism of death
          •  Determining medical history

          •  Correlating wounding and object producing the wounds

          •  Determining the time interval between wounds received

             and death

          •  Establishing the sequence of events

          •  Retrieving evidence and article(s) involved in death

          •  Obtaining  specimens  for  toxicology  and  other  relevant
             information




          The conventional method of examination is carried out

          within 2-3 working days following death. There is no fixed

          time as to how long it will take. The full postmortem ex-

          amination can be described in the following stages:



          1. Receiving a request letter

          2. Identification

          3. External examination




                                                           109]]></page><page Index="111"><![CDATA[4. Internal examination (inspection of internal organs of

                the body)

                5. Special examinations/tests

                6. An account of the findings
                Modern imaging techniques are of increasing importance

                in post-mortem investigations due to multiple advantages;

                data can be stored digitally and accessed at any time; 3D

                images can be reconstructed and can explain complex cas-

                es to non-forensic persons. However, the limitations of the

                same depend on the technique employed.



                Plain X-Rays




                Fig. 1. Schematic diagram of a
                roentgenogram; the X-ray

                beam is produced by the cathode

                (A), focused through the tissue
                in question allowing differing

                densities of the tissue to produce
                a greyscale mosaic (B) When the

                plate is fully exposed, creates the
                roentgenogram, or “plain X-ray”

                (C). Photo via Forensic Pathology

                Reviews, Vol. 4.



                The application of radiology in cases of medicolegal in-

                terest originated with  Wilhelm Roentgen’s discovery of

                X-rays (1895).  The radiological assessment of the body

                is produced by collimated X-ray beams (possessing wave-

                length in the range of 10–8m) focusing on the anatomical

                region in question, creating an image through the reaction
                between the beam and silver emulsion present on a photo-

                graphic plate.



                                                             110]]></page><page Index="112"><![CDATA[The  reduced  silver  particles  produce  black  areas  (radio-

             lucency), and the inability to penetrate tissues results in

             the absence of reduction and hence, a white (radiopaque)

             area.  The result is a greyscale mosaic (the roentgeno-
             gram image) known commonly, although incorrectly, as

             an  “X-ray” (Fig. 1). Plain X-rays have been used for

             the  purpose  of  identification,  determining the cause of

             death, evidence of non-accidental injury, and locating

             foreign objects. Another advantage includes the ability

             to produce multiple copies. A major disadvantage is that

             the image is 2D.


             Fluoroscopy

             Fluoroscopy is a mobile, rapid means of examining bod-

             ies, offering real-time examination. The units produce a

             continuous, low-power X-ray beam focused on the re-

             gion in question, employed during cadaver examination,

             bone trauma, metal projectiles, fragments, etc.  The flu-
             oroscopic fields of view are however, narrow, have low

             resolution, and don’t have the ability to create “copies”.




             Angiography

             Angiography is a technique used to visualize the lumen

             of blood vessels and organs (with a particular interest in

             arteries, veins, and the heart chambers), done by inject-
             ing a radiopaque agent into blood vessels and imaging it

             using X-ray based techniques. However, images are dif-

             ficult to interpret and may not provide any information

             that cannot be gleaned through CT (Computed Tomog-

             raphy)/MRI (Magnetic Resonance Imaging).  The pro-

             cess is slow, time-consuming, and operator-dependent.




                                                             111]]></page><page Index="113"><![CDATA[Ultrasonography

                Like  fluoroscopy, it  allows real-time examination through

                the production of sound waves within the ultrasound

                range (3.5-7 MHz).  When the wave contacts an interface
                between tissues of differing densities, the wave is reflected,

                refracted, or absorbed, received through a probe unit and

                processed to form an image. Although user-safe, portable,

                and inexpensive, the technique has only been applied in

                research and is superseded by MRI. It occasionally plays a

                role in forensic pathology.


                Computed Tomography

                CT was developed in 1972 as a means of radiologically

                producing thin transverse sectional images through a body.

                It requires a collimated X-ray beam to be passed and de-

                tected using a circular array of photomultiplier tubes. The

                narrower the scan diameters, the more accurate the image.

                The result is a rapidly-produced full body scan image (Fig
                2).  The  disadvantages  include radiological exposure risk,

                cost, and digital image streaking caused by the presence of

                metal in the body.











                Fig.2.Scanograms -

                rapidly produced body scan of large
                anatomical regions, produced through by

                the computed tomography scanner Photo

                via Forensic Pathology Reviews, Vol. 4










                                                            112]]></page><page Index="114"><![CDATA[Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI Scan)

          Developed  in  1980  by  P.  Lauterbur  and  P.  Mansfield,  MRI

          utilizes the natural, rotational behavior of H+ ions and

          employs  the application  of two  strong,  perpendicular,  ex-
          ternal magnetic fields.  The changes in frequency are de-

          tected, producing a magnetic resonance signal, forming

          the basis of the image.

          The technique holds no radiation exposure risk, although

          it must be certain that the body examined does not con-

          tain metal. The degree of image resolution provided is ex-

          cellent.


          REFERENCES:

          •  May 6, 2016. PATIENT ADVOCACY - Forensic Med-

              icine. Retrieved from http://lhmc-hosp.gov.in/WriteRe-

              adData/l892s/PATIENT%20ADVOCACY%20Foren-

              sic%20Medicine%2006%2005%2016.pdf

          •  Swift B. & Rutty G. N., Recent Advances in Postmortem
              Forensic  Radiology. Humana  Press Inc. Retrieved from

              http://eknygos.lsmuni.lt/springer/661/355-404.pdf

          •  Grabherr S., Egger C.,  Vilarino R., Campana L., Me-

              lissa Jotterand M., & Dedouita F. June 7, 2017. Mod-

              ern  post-mortem  imaging.  Retrieved  from  https://

              www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6197109/\

























                                                             113]]></page><page Index="115"><![CDATA[A NEW DIMENSION IN


                                              FORENSICS











                                                                       Ms. Blessy John Kaalla



                3D printing or additive manufacturing is a method for

                creating  a  three-dimensional  object  layer-by-layer  using  a

                computer-created design.
                The application of 3D printing in the field of medicine and

                dentistry has skyrocketed in recent years because of its abil-

                ity to produce highly realistic physical 3D Structures of the

                computer- aided design model.




                How does a 3D printer work?



                MODELING: Digital imaging and communications in

                medicine images are used to create 3D printed models us-

                ing  different  modeling  softwares.  3D  printers  accept  stan-

                dard tessellation language file format that defines surfaces

                like a collection of triangles that fits together like a puzzle.

                We can design our model by using basic shapes and struc-

                tures.  The additive manufacturing file format is a newer
                format approved by ASTM(American Society for  Testing

                and Materials) International to incorporate surface texture

                color and material properties.




                SLICING:  The 3D printing software scans and slices the

                model so that the printer understands the shape and how

                to print it.
                The filament is the material that the models are printed

                from such as plastics, metals and ceramic.



                                                            114]]></page><page Index="116"><![CDATA[The printer has a printing plate that moves up and down.

          The print head that moves in any direction has a heating

          element when the filament is fed, it melts and draws the

          first slice outline and then fills it in. Layers are deposited to
          generate the 3D model.

          The quality of 3D printers depends on the technology. Ste-

          reolithography was considered to be the most accurate as

          it provides better resolution by utilizing a scanning laser to

          fuse fine powder material generating a layer-by-layer struc-

          ture, and the light-sensitive polymer is cured and hardened

          in a UV oven.



          APPLICATIONS:




          1. DOCUMENTATION

          Human remains offer conclusive proof in the area of fo-

          rensics,  the  documentation  is  mostly  done  in  the  form  of

          photographs and electronic copies owing to legal and eth-
          ical problems. 3D printing of human remains can convey

          important details to the court and jury.
























          3D Printed models of mandible and skull for documentation

          Credits:https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-
                                      S2666964121000011-gr1.jpg






                                                             115]]></page><page Index="117"><![CDATA[It can be transported for consultation without transporting

                the remains. During a virtual autopsy, files are acquired

                in  DICOM(Digital Imaging and  Communications in  Med-

                icine) files and 3D models in their hands, and forensic ex-
                perts can revisit the case without exhumation. Printed mod-

                els may soon be a part of ante-mortem for comparative

                human identification.




                2. HUMAN IDENTIFICATION

                An accurate model of the maxilla and mandible dentition

                may be  useful in age  estimation and  sex determination. A
                3D model obtained from postmortem computed tomogra-

                phy helps to minimize difficulties in traditional autopsies

                such as examination due to rigor mortis or lack of proper

                visualization. 3D models of skull, sinuses, face, fingerprints,

                lip prints ,and palatal aid in identification and can serve as

                evidence in the future.


























                A) 3D printed upper and lower dentition for morphometric anal-

                ysis,  (B)3D printed  rugae  (C)  3D  printed  lips  for  coloscopy  (D)3D
                printed face for future referral (E) 3D printed mandible (F) 3D

                                                      printed Palm.
                Credits:https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-

                                           S2666964121000011-gr2.jpg




                                                             116]]></page><page Index="118"><![CDATA[3. BITEMARKS AND PATTERN ANALYSIS

          Bite marks analysis is evaluated on a comparative basis in
          which morphological features of dentition and bite marks

          are matched. 3D printing enables storage of alleged suspect

          dentition  which  can  be  used for  future  analysis  by  retriev-

          ing it. Bite marks might be scanned from the skin, foodstuff

          ,and objects enabling 3D or printed comparisons. Impres-

          sion evidence recovery like tire, footwear impression, tool

          mark analysis 3D model can be scaled up and printed to
          aid in the investigation and can be used for courtroom pre-

          sentation.


























          (A) 3D printed bite-mark on hand(top) analysis of bite-mark(bot-

                                                       tom)
                           (B) 3D printed footwear pattern impression.

          Credits:https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-

                                      S2666964121000011-gr4.jpg



          4. FACIAL RECONSTRUCTION

          A method of recreating an individual’s face from skeletal

          remains by utilizing tissue markers. Printing skulls from

          computed tomography enables reconstruction of the face
          without damage to the original skull of anthropological or

          archaeological value.





                                                             117]]></page><page Index="119"><![CDATA[5. BALLISTIC RECONSTRUCTION

                Fired bullets can be scanned and 3D printed. They can be
                compared to check for deformation. Bullet trajectories can

                be generated using digital imaging techniques, which can

                be printed for presenting as evidence and demonstrating a

                case scenario.























                3D  printed  bullets  unfired  bullets  and  fired  and  deformed  bul-

                                                      lets(left right)
                credits:https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-

                                           S2666964121000011-gr5.jpg




                6. DISASTER VICTIM IDENTIFICATION
                CT(Computed  Tomography) scan of severely charred re-

                mains of maxillary and mandibular teeth can be used for

                identification in disaster victim identification. 3D scanning

                of the remains will facilitate the handling and analysis of

                burnt remains and court presentation.




                7.      CRIME          AND          ACCIDENT             SCENE           RECONSTRUC-
                TION

                3D  printing  of  various  vehicle  models  in  case  of  accident

                reconstruction  can  aid  in  demonstrating  the  relationship

                between the collided vehicles.







                                                            118]]></page><page Index="120"><![CDATA[ADVANTAGES:
          1. Visual representation of anatomy in court.

          2. 3D printed evidence can be revisited and re-evaluated in

              case of decomposition, burial  ,or destruction of original

              evidence.

          3. Better visualization




          DISADVANTAGES:
          1. The accuracy of 3D prints leads to issues of admissibility

              in court.

          2. Easily accessible as it can be shared, downloaded, mod-

              ified ,and printed.

          3. Typical characteristics cannot be replicated.



          CONCLUSION:

          3D Printing allows for better visualization, interpretation

          ,and  understanding.  It is  a humanitarian approach as  the

          evidence  is reconstructed  without  touching or damaging

          the evidence.3D printing technology in India is still in the

          initial stages but newer methods can transform its applica-
          tion in the field of forensics.




          REFERENCE:

          •  Jani, G., Johnson, A., Marques, J., & Franco, A. (2021).

              Three-dimensional(3D) printing in forensic science–An

              emerging technology in India. Annals of 3D Printed Medi-

              cine,  1,  100006.  Retrieved  from  https://doi.org/10.1016/j.
              stlm.2021.100006














                                                             119]]></page><page Index="121"><![CDATA[-
































                               LITERATURE REVIEW

















         •  Prostitution is a “profession”: recommendations and

             directions by the supreme court

         •  The relation between gunshot residue particle size


             and boltzmann distribution




































                                                             120]]></page><page Index="122"><![CDATA[PROSTITUTION IS A



                                        “PROFESSION”:



                         RECOMMENDATIONS AND



                                  DIRECTIONS BY THE


                                     SUPREME COURT










           Ms. Swetha Ann Mathew



























           Prostitution, the oldest profession in the world, was never
           an unfamiliar concept to the Indians. Questions regarding

           dignity, poverty, rights, diseases, and unemployment have

           always  been  prevalent  in  the  area.  It’s  been  more  than  a

           decade since the first time the apex court set out to im-

           prove the lives of sex workers after the case of Budhadev

           Karmaskar v State of West Bengal, 2011.



           “Sex workers are entitled to equal protection of the law.

           Criminal law must apply equally in all cases on the basis

           of age and consent. When it is clear that the sex worker is

           an adult and is participating with consent, the police must

           refrain from interfering or taking any criminal action. It



                                                           121]]></page><page Index="123"><![CDATA[need not be gainsaid that notwithstanding the profession,
                 every individual in this country has the right to a dig-

                 nified life under Article 21 of the Constitution,”  quot-

                 ed the three-bench judge consisting of L Nageswara Rao,

                 BR Gavai, and AS Bopanna. Hence on the 19th of May,

                 2022  the  Supreme  court  recognised  sex  work  as  a “pro-

                 fession” and issued commendable guidelines to give these

                 sex workers equal protection under the law.



                 So, what is this profusion of processes ordered by the su-

                 preme court to uplift these women?


























                 https://www.nbcnews.com/think/opinion/end-sex-trafficking-

                                    stop-arresting-sex-workers-ncna869156
                 •  Firstly, the supreme court suggested that; A sex worker,

                     who is a victim of sexual assault should be treated the

                     way any sexual assault victim is treated, in accordance

                     with Section 357C of CrPC (Criminal Procedure Code).

                 •  The  court  also  suggested  that  children  of  sex  workers
                     should  not  be  forcibly  separated  from  their  mothers

                     merely on the basis that she’s engaged in the sex trade.

                     A test could be conducted to prove the parentage of the

                     minor before making stigmatised assumptions.





                                                            122]]></page><page Index="124"><![CDATA[•  Since “voluntary sex work is not illegal [ Immoral  Traf-

               fic (Prevention) Act,1956] and only running the brothel

               is unlawful”, sex workers should not be arrested, pe-

               nalised, harassed, or victimised during police raids on a

               brothel.

           •  The fourth suggestion pertained to involve sex workers

               or their representatives while formulating policies for
               them. The central and state governments have to ensure

               the involvement of these workers in the decision-mak-

               ing panel.

           •  Furthermore, it also suggested employing the Legal Ser-

               vices Authority to conduct workshops to educate the

               sex workers about their rights, obligations to the police,
               and their access to the judicial system.

           •  The directions endorsed by the court to the law enforce-

               ment agencies require them to be sensitised to the right

               of sex workers.

           •  The police should not verbally or physically abuse sex

               workers.  The basic protection of human decency and
               dignity will extend to sex workers and their children.

               They will not be deprived of their right to live a digni-

               fied life.

           •  Also, measures that a sex worker employs for their

               health and safety must neither br construed as an of-

               fence or as evidence of commission of that offence.

           •  Another direction was aimed at the Press Council of
               India stating that “utmost care should be taken to not

               reveal the identities of sex workers, during arrest, raid

               and rescue operations, whether as victims or accused

               and not publish or telecast any photo that would result

               in disclosure of such identities”, failing at which will




                                                            123]]></page><page Index="125"><![CDATA[be punishable under  Section 354C of IPC (Indian Penal

                Code).

                The apex court also added that the orders so passed [un-

                der article 142 of the constitution] would hold the field

                until the time the Union Government comes up with a leg-

                islation. The union govt. is expected to give its response
                to these recommendations at the next hearing, dated 27th

                of July 2022.

                This decision by the Supreme Court is truly historic in-

                deed. Even though the aspect of ‘legal sex work’ has been

                in  ambiguity,  examples  of countries like  Germany,  Neth-

                erlands, France, Greece that have legalised the profession
                gives us hope that one day, India too will have better living

                conditions for sex workers. Implementing and enforcing

                the laws will help us get past the brunt stigma and discrim-

                ination long cemented with the profession of prostitution.




                REFERENCES:

                1. Sinha, A.N., [n.d].The problem of prostitution an Indi-
                    an prespective.Pune,India:legalserviceindia.com, https://

                    www.legalserviceindia.com

                2. Image1 by Nicole Figueroa, https://medium.com/@

                    nfigueroa114

                3. Jain, A., [2022]. Supreme Court order on sex work his-

                    toric, but execution will be the real hurdle. Mumbai,

                    India: The Print. https://theprint.in
                4. Mandhani, A., [2022]. Sex work not illegal? Should sex

                    workers be arrested?’ 4 questions SC has asked Modi

                    govt. Mumbai, India: The Print. https://theprint.in

                5. Image2 by The Hindu, https://www.thehindu.com







                                                            124]]></page><page Index="126"><![CDATA[THE RELATION BETWEEN


                                   GUNSHOT RESIDUE



                                   PARTICLE SIZE AND



                        BOLTZMANN DISTRIBUTION












             Ms. Akshara B





           Gunshot residue (GSR) is also commonly known as car-

           tridge discharge residue (CDR) or gunfire residue (GFR)

           or firearm discharge residue (FDR). GSR is an important

           form of trace evidence that would pave the way for inves-
           tigation. GSR is found in solid, liquid, or gaseous state

           under high exothermic reactions due to high temperature

           and pressure and  is any mixture of burnt and unburnt ma-

           terials that originate from a firing gun and get deposited

           on the hands, or clothes of the person who discharges the

           firearm. The residue can include substances from primer,

           projectile, cartridge cases, etc. Gunshot residue can travel
           over 3-5 feet (0.9-1.5m).

           GSR analysis is majorly done to determine whether a fire-

           arm has been used. Determination of the structural dis-

           tribution of GSR would help in its analysis. Primer par-

           ticles contain lead (Pb), barium (Ba), and antimony (Sb)

           and hence they are analyzed by using sodium rhodizonate

           test scanning electron microscopy with energy dispersive
           x-ray detection. According to various studies, it is found

           that  GSR consists  of  spherical  particles  as  a  result  of  ran-

           dom distribution. But under this study, it describes GSR




                                                          125]]></page><page Index="127"><![CDATA[particles based on a specific distribution function.  The

                Boltzmann distribution function is the most basic and

                probable principle, the dimensional size distribution of
                GSR particles was analyzed according to this principle.




                METHOD USED AND ANALYSIS

                Sarsilmaz Kilinc (9mm)2000 mega-brand semiautomat-

                ic pistol was used for test firing, with full metal jacket

                cartridges  that were produced by  a  9  mm  x 19 mm  Par-

                abellum-type MKE, Geco, S&B,  WIN, and LIBRA.  The
                samples were collected from the shooter’s right hand (es-

                pecially from regions of the thumb and index finger) with

                the help of double-sided adhesive tape glued to aluminum

                stubs. Before each shot, the weapon barrel was cleaned

                by mechanical cleaning or even in an ultrasonic bath of

                ethanol and deionized water before being dried with dry

                nitrogen gas. The collected GSRs were analyzed using the
                specified techniques.



























                Figure 1. GSR particles of different sizes formed by fragmenta-

                                       tion splitting and external factors.

                https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/20961790.2020.
                                                         1713433




                                                             126]]></page><page Index="128"><![CDATA[Figure 2 .GSR particle size measurement(A), EDS spectrum(B).
           https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/20961790.2020.1713

                                                       433



           DIMENSIONAL ANALYSIS

           The dimensional classes of GSR are obtained using the

           sizes (r_1) of the primary particles of the GSR and the to-

           tal number of particles (m_1). The density of the primary

           class can be determined from r_k = r_1 based on basis of

           Enskog–Boltzmann’s theory, the dimensional distribution
           ratio of the GSR particles depends on splitting–merging

           and external factors.

           According to the study the size distribution of the dimen-

           sional classes was found to be similar to that of the in-

           verse square method (Boltzmann distribution).

           The results are based on:

           •  merging effect of adhesion forces.
           •  the effect of unbalanced forces split due to excess sur-

               face energy

           •  fragmentation because of external.




           BOLTZMANN DISTRIBUTION

           The basic equation for the number of molecules with vari-

           able velocities and energies is found in the Boltzmann




                                                             127]]></page><page Index="129"><![CDATA[distribution. Gas molecules move at various velocities and

                in  various  directions  for  the  model  as  it  is  based  on  ki-

                netic molecular  theory. The distance of each molecule to

                its starting point is proportional to the magnitude of the

                molecular velocity, and hence the molecule behaves iso-
                tropically.

                If molecules are small then their velocity increases rapid-

                ly, therefore, the velocities of molecules at the same tem-

                perature are inversely proportional to the square root of

                molecular masses.  The results experimentally prove Gra-

                ham’s law.



                MATLAB COMPUTER PROGRAM

                The result obtained through the experiment was trans-

                formed into data that are converted as model curves. The

                data in the intervals showed behavior that conformed to

                the inverse square method (Boltzmann distribution).
































                               Figure 3. Fit curve of variation of GSR particle.

                https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/20961790.2020.
                                                         1713433




                                                           128]]></page><page Index="130"><![CDATA[CONCLUSION

            This was an experimental study that gave a briefing about

            the quantitative analysis of particle size distribution prop-
            erties of GSR. A GSR model was created strictly based

            on Boltzmann distribution.  The data obtained through

            analysis in a simplified system were made into different

            groups.  The particle size distribution was found to be

            consistent according to Boltzmann kinetic equation.  The

            data created were analyzed using the MATLAB program

            wherein the results gave an overall outline for all GSR
            particles. If further improvements are made to this study,

            then that would help us to compare different brands and

            scales of ammunition.




            REFERENCES:

            •  Ilker Kara, 2022, The relationship between gunshot-res-

               idue particle size and Boltzmann distribution Retrieved
               from           https://doi.org/10.1080/20961790.2020.171343

               3

            •  G M  Wolten; R S Nesbitt, 1980, Mechanism of Gun-

               shot  Residue  particles,  Retrieved  from  https://www.

               ojp.gov/ncjrs/virtual-library/abstracts/mechanism-gun-

               shot-residue-particle-formation.

            •  Simpson,  2008, Gunshot  residue analysis on  single
               gunpowder particle, Retrieved from https://www.acs.

               org/content/acs/en/pressroom/newsreleases/2008/april/

               crime-scene-investigations-gunshot-residue-analy-

               sis-on-a-single-gunpowder-particle.html













                                                            129]]></page><page Index="131"><![CDATA[STATISTICAL DATA















         •  A study to identify the factors influencing suicide


             in different states of India

         •  Trend analysis of incidents involving drugs/nar-

             cotics as per NIBRS data








































                                                             130]]></page><page Index="132"><![CDATA[A STUDY TO IDENTIFY THE


        FACTORS                             INFLUENCING                                    SUICIDE



                   IN DIFFERENT STATES OF INDIA











         Ms. Ashritha S M

         Mr. Riki Leadingson Siangshai
         Mr. Abhishek M Sasi




         INTRODUCTION

         Suicide is defined as a conscious try to harm oneself with a

         fatal result. This can be break-free attempted suicide during

         which a selected try to kill was made but was unsuccessful

         and self-harm, which could be a blanket term for self-in-

         flicted non-fatal injury irrespective of the purpose.
         The male-female ratio has remained constant at roughly

         1.4 to 1. Suicide rates differ dramatically throughout the

         country.  Every  year,  India  loses around 100,000  individu-

         als to suicide. Suicide rates have risen from 7.9 to 10.8 per

         100,000 during the previous twenty years.



         AIM AND OBJECTIVES OF THE STUDY

         1. To determine the factors affecting females and males to

             commit suicide

         2. To determine the factors affecting males to commit sui-

             cide

         3. To determine the factors affecting females to commit sui-
             cide




         METHODOLOGY

         Web databases were searched for cases registered in Delhi,



                                                            131]]></page><page Index="133"><![CDATA[Karnataka, and Maharashtra under section 309 of the Kar-

                nataka, and Maharashtra under section 309 of the Indian

                Penal code.

                Cases during the period 2000 to 2021 were chosen. A total
                of 50 cases of attempts to suicide were studied per state.

                Each factor behind the attempt of suicide was listed.

                All the factors were studied in a tabulated form.

                The cases were studied on the following basis:

                •  Gender

                •  Reason for attempting suicide
                •  Method of suicide attempted

                •  Material used for attempting suicide

                •  Factors affecting suicide

                •  The year the suicide was attempted

                These details help us to understand the factors and which

                gender is more prone to attempt suicide.



                FINDINGS FOR THE STATE OF DELHI

                There were an equal number of male and female instances

                in Delhi. 90% of males attempted suicide for reasons such

                as mental problems, while  10% attempted  suicide due to

                psychiatric disease and other factors such as fear of be-

                ing prosecuted by the high court for theft, rape, and other
                crimes.


























                                                            132]]></page><page Index="134"><![CDATA[50% of females attempted suicide as a result of physical

          and emotional abuse from coworkers, landlords, etc. 40%

          attempted suicide due to harassment from spouses, in-laws,

          false accusations of extra-marital affairs, etc., and 10%

          were due to psychological issues and exam stress.


























          3% attempted suicide by slitting the neck and wrist with

          a knife, 1% attempted suicide by jumping into ricer, 10%

          by overdosing on drugs, 7% by consuming poison, 3%

          by consuming phenyl, 5% by jumping on metro tracks,

          6%  by  hanging,  9%  by  jumping  from  tall  buildings,  6%
          by self-immolation, 2% by self-strangulation, and 1% by

          shooting using a firearm.16% of victims tried to commit

          suicide due to depression, 14% due to mental stress, 2%

          due to the work and new rules brought about by the gov-

          ernment, 4% due to being sexually harassed, 1% due to

          psychiatric problems, 7% due to being mentally disturbed,
          1% were in jail due to getting caught in crimes, 2% due to

          false  accusations,  and  1%  due  to  having  a  break  up  with

          their spouse.













                                                           133]]></page><page Index="135"><![CDATA[FINDINGS FOR THE STATE OF KARNATAKA

                76% were males, and 24% were females.
























                50% of victims attempted suicide due to guilt after the com-

                mission  of  a  heinous  crime,  30%  were  due  to  depression,
                10% were due to an unstable mindset during the attempt,

                4%  due  to  financial  crisis,  4%  due  to family  issues,  and

                2% due to prevailing sickness.



























                24% attempts were made by poisoning, 22% by self-stab-
                bing, 18% by cutting wrist and neck, 14% by hanging, 8%

                by jumping into rivers, 8% by jumping in wells, 2% by

                self-injection of drugs, and 4% reason was unknown.




                FINDINGS FOR THE STATE OF MAHARASHTRA

                52% were males, and 48% were females.





                                                            134]]></page><page Index="136"><![CDATA[25% were due to depression, 15% due to family problems,
         15% due to relationship issues, 15% were due to paramour

         relationships, 10% were due to financial problems, 10%

         were due to harassment, and 10% reasons were not clearly

         stated.





























          41% of suicide attempts were committed by hanging, 32%

          by intoxication with drugs, 9% by jumping from tall build-

          ings, 6% were by jumping in front of vehicles, 6% by cut-

          ting wrist or neck, and 6% were by unclear means.













                                                            135]]></page><page Index="137"><![CDATA[REFERENCES:

                •  Vijayakumar, L. (2010). Indian research on suicide. In-

                    dian Journal of Psychiatry, 52(7), 291. Retrieved from

                    https://doi.org/10.4103/0019-5545.69255

                •  Gutti, S., Koppisetty, S. S., Paladugu, S., Kumar Reddy,
                    M. M., Murali Krishna, N., & Rama Rao, N. (2019). A

                    Case Control Study on Factors Influencing Suicide At-

                    tempts. Indian Journal of Pharmacy Practice, 13(1), 36–

                    41. Retrieved from https://doi.org/10.5530/ijopp.13.1.6

                 •  Gururaj, G. (2004). Risk factors for completed suicide.

                    Retrieved from Https://Nimhans.Ac.In/. https://nim-

                    hans.ac.in/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/Risk_factors_
                    for_completed_suicides.pdf

                 •  Amor, C. B. (2020, March 24).  WHY IS  THE SUI-

                    CIDE  RATE  HIGHER  IN  MEN  THAN IN  WOMEN

                     Retrieved          from         Https://Www.Academia.Edu/.https://

                     www.academia.edu/42306120/WHY_IS_THE_SUI-

                     CIDE_RATE_HIGHER_IN_MEN_THAN_IN_WOM-

                     EN


                                            MYTH BUSTERS




                                            Myth: For detection of blood in scene

                                            of crime, investigators use blue light.

                                            Fact: Usually in television only the use of

                                            blue  light  is showcased.  In  fact  luminol

                                            along with special lighting ( Alternative

                                            light source) is required for the samples

                                            to get detected.










                                                             136]]></page><page Index="138"><![CDATA[TREND ANALYSIS OF



                              INCIDENTS INVOLVING



                        DRUGS/NARCOTICS AS PER



                                            NIBRS DATA












           Ms. Arsha Sahadevan




         The National Incident-Based Reporting System (NIBRS) is

         a data collation system provided by the Federal Bureau of

         Investigation (FBI) to serve as a national crime database for

         the United States. It aims to report crime incidents while also
         looking into the context of such crimes to identify informa-

         tion like the day and time of the crime, the victim-offender

         relationships, and so forth.  The data contained in NIBRS

         is a collective effort of the various law enforcement agen-

         cies placed across several states in the U.S. NIBRS works

         in pursuit of providing better-policing strategies, filling in

         gaps in existing data, and creating safer communities. It is
         a part of the FBI’s Uniform Crime Reporting (UCR) pro-

         gram. NIBRS issues the report annually. A broad classifica-

         tion of the crimes reported includes crimes against persons,

         crimes against property, and crimes against society.




         Following are the statistics concerning incidents involv-

          ing seized drugs/narcotics for the years 2016, 2017, 2018,
          2019, and 2020 as per NIBRS reports:








                                                            137]]></page><page Index="139"><![CDATA[•  In 2016, the total offenses concerning drugs/narcot-

                    ics amounted to 783,205 cases.  This count increased

                    to  874,003  for  the  year  2017.  A  total  of  936,757  cas-

                    es were reported in the year 2018.  The year 2019 saw
                    an increase in the drug/narcotic offenses reported, with

                    1,038,516 being the total count. The recently published

                    report for the year 2020 showed a total of 1,039,388

                    offenses concerning drugs/narcotics.
































                The above chart shows a constant increase in the total re-

                ported offenses throughout the five-year timeline.

                The below series of pie charts depict the trends concerning

                the suspected drug type seized in the reported drug/narcot-

                ics cases.

                In 2017, out of the total 594,625 incidents involving drugs/
                narcotics seized by their suspected drug type, marijuana

                accounted for 311,808  cases. 117,064 cases involved am-

                phetamines, 55,576 involved heroin, and 56,894 involved

                cocaine of different forms.









                                                             138]]></page><page Index="140"><![CDATA[In 2018, there were 643,890 incidents involving seized

         drugs/narcotics. Among these, 344,167 cases involved mar-

         ijuana, 147,566 involved amphetamines, 55,899 involved

         heroin, and 60,877 involved cocaine of different forms.
































         In 2019, there were 710,812 incidents involving seized

         drugs/narcotics, out of which 351,550 cases involved mar-

         ijuana, 194,493 involved amphetamines, 63,523 involved
          heroin, and 73,481 involved cocaine of different forms.











                                                           139]]></page><page Index="141"><![CDATA[The recent 2020 report showed a total of 708,513 incidents

                involving seized drugs/narcotics, out of which 345,308 cas-

                es involved marijuana, 210,881 involved amphetamines,

                67,834 involved heroin, and 65,297 involved cocaine of

                different forms.
































                On analyzing the data regarding the suspected drug type

                seized in such cases involving drug/narcotics, a substantial

                increase in the number of unknown type drugs seized can

                be observed. This is indicative of the rise in the synthesis of

                New Psychoactive Substances (NPS) or designer drugs, as
                is commonly known.






                                                            140]]></page><page Index="142"><![CDATA[Concerning the juvenile age group’s involvement in drug/

          narcotic offenses, the following points were deduced:
          •  In 2016, juveniles (anyone below 18 years of age) ac-

             counted for 7.9% of the offenses involving drugs/narcot-

             ics, while adults accounted for the rest.

          •  In 2017, juveniles accounted for 7.6% of the reported of-

             fenses that involved drugs/narcotics.

          •  The year 2018 saw a marginal decrease in the involve-

             ment of juveniles in drugs/narcotics offenses, with the
             age  group  being  accountable  for  7.0%  of  the  total  of-

             fenses.

          •  In 2019, 6.83% of the offenses involved juveniles, and

             this reduced to 5.4% in 2020.

          •  As  for  the  overall  trend,  there  was  a  constant  decline

             in the number of juvenile offenders in cases involving

             drugs/narcotics.



          The above data is not an accurate measure of the crimes

          since, even now, many or few states do not provide a com-

          plete account of the cases being reported. The FBI is per-

          sistently working to increase the rate of reporting crimes,

          enabling them to provide valid and valuable data to law

          enforcement personnel.



          REFERENCES:

          •  Federal Bureau of Investigation. (2019). NIBRS. Feder-

             al  Bureau  of  Investigation.  Retrieved  from  https://www.

             fbi.gov/services/cjis/ucr/nibrs

          •  Data  Tables. (n.d.). FBI. Retrieved from https://ucr.fbi.

             gov/nibrs/2016/tables/data-tables
          •  Data  Tables. (n.d.). FBI. Retrieved from https://ucr.fbi.

             gov/nibrs/2017/tables/data-tables



                                                             141]]></page><page Index="143"><![CDATA[•   Data  Tables. (n.d.). FBI. Retrieved from https://ucr.fbi.

                     gov/nibrs/2018/tables/data-tables

                 •  Data  Tables. (n.d.). FBI. Retrieved from https://ucr.fbi.

                     gov/nibrs/2019/tables/data-tables

                 •  (2021).  Cloud.gov.  Retrieved from https://crime-da-

                     ta-explorer.app.cloud.gov/pages/downloads

























                                            FACTS !




                                            Hair roots can help identify gender? Hair

                                            found at a crime scene can be very help-
                                            ful in terms of evidence, but only the hair

                                            root contains a person’s DNA and that

                                            can help determine a person’s gender.
































                                                            142]]></page><page Index="144"><![CDATA[WORD SEARCH











      Ms. Supriya P V
      Ms. Aditi S Pai

      Ms. Natasha Jennifer Easu






      Z     R      H      U      M       A      N       N       S      P     U      R       P       L      E     R


      I     A      O       S     D       K      G       H       N      E      T     A       L      U      X      O


      T     C      M       T     U       N       T      A       Y      L     O      R       B      M       P     H


      C     X       I     D       C      H      A       R       R      E     D      Z       S       I      E     T


      I     J      C       L      K      A      R       E       C      S      I     V       R      N       R     L


      L     T       I      P      V      R       F      D       R      U     G       S      A      O       T     A


      E      I     D      O       I      L      D       N       A      H      Y     K       L       X     O      S


     D      N      E       T      R      E       T      R       O      L     D      U       P       L      P     K


      S     X      P       Y      T      Y      G       N       R       I    Z       S      M      A       I     C



     U      A      S      U      O       F      W        I      K      F      T     A       E       T     N      O


      P     R      U      D       P      O      H       N       S      T     Q      N       X       E      I     R


      R     H      F      A       S      B      P       A       G      B      T      S      E      N      O      O


     O      T      O       J      Y      G      O       L       O      C      I     X       O       T     N      O



      C     N       I     O       I      S      C       E       V       I     S      I      B       L      E     A


      R     A      L       L     U       D       E      M       O      M A          H       A       Z     A      R







                                                            143]]></page><page Index="145"><![CDATA[Hidden Words











      1. The essential facts that prove that a crime has been committed

      2. Section 45 of Indian Evidence Act


      3. Proof of procedures observed in revenue case

      4. Bones are collected in containers containing _____

      5. Virtual autopsy is also called _______


      6. Ninhydrin reacts with amino acids present in the fingerprint res-

          idue to form a dye called ________


      7. Detection and identification of presence of drugs and poisons in

          body fluids, tissues and organs comes under which branch of fo-

          rensic science?


      8. ______ are known handwriting samples used for comparison

          with questioned documents


      9. Killing of one human being by another

      10.  Polyvinyl acetate is used to strengthen edges of ________ doc-

          uments


      11.  Fingerprints that cannot be seen

      12.  Ratio of distance traveled by solute to distance traveled by sol-

          vent


      13.  Innermost layer of hair shaft

      14.  _______ refers to the internal organs of the abdominal, thorac-

          ic and pelvic cavities.


      15.  A bioweapon released in US in 2001











                                                          144]]></page><page Index="146"><![CDATA[CONTRIBUTORS                                                                                                        CONTRIBUTORS








                                                 2019 Batch





             1. Ms. Aakanksha Sunil - 19LS3A1001

             2. Ms. Adheena Shibu - 19LS3A1002
             3. Ms. Ann Mariya Thomas - 19LS3A1003

             4. Ms. Catherine Maria Johny - 19LS3A1004

             5. Ms. Gayathri L Nair - 19LS3A1007

             6. Ms. Jocelyn Kunju John - 19LS3A1009

             7. Ms. Litzia Sebastian - 19LS3A1010

             8. Ms. Nivya George - 19LS3A1011

             9. Mr. Thomas Prince Kuruppen Parambil - 19LS3A1013
             10.  Mr. Abhishek M Sasi - 19LS3H1016

             11.  Ms. Aishwarya P.V - 19LS3H1017

             12.  Ms. Arya K.S - 19LS3H1018

             13.  Ms. Ashritha S M - 19LS3H1019

             14.  Ms. Sruthi Evangeline Kali - 19LS3H1020

             15.  Mr. Joseph J. Kachappally - 19LS3H1023

             16.  Mr. Justin Babu - 19LS3H1024
             17.  Ms. Krishnapriya - 19LS3H1025

             18.  Ms. Lorraine Tissan - 19LS3H1026

             19.  Mr. Sharath Richard - 19LS3H1029

             20.  Ms. Umme Salma Razak - 19LS3H1030

             21.  Ms. Amulya M - 19LS3K1031

             22.  Ms. Harshitha M V - 19LS3A1033

             23.  Ms. Faiza Farheen - 19LS3A1039
             24.  Mr. Neeraj P.B - 19LS3A1040

             25.  Mr. Fahed Bin Abdul Aziz K - 19LS3A1044

             26.  Mr. Riki Leadingson Siangshai - 19LS3A1045




                                                         145]]></page><page Index="147"><![CDATA[CONTRIBUTORS                 CONTRIBUTORS








                                               2020 Batch





                  1. Ms. Arsha Sahadevan - 20LS3A1008

                  2. Ms. Rainelle R. Dennesen - 20LS3A1032
                  3. Ms. Supriya PV - 20LS3A1035

                  4. Ms. Aditi S Pai - 20LS3H1037

                  5. Ms. Natasha Jennifer Easu - 20LS3H1043

                  6. Ms. Swetha Ann Mathew - 20LS3H1050

                  7. Ms. Blessy John Kaalla - 20LS3K1053

                  8. Ms. Neha Elsa John - 20LS3A1065

                  9. Ms. Akshara B - 20LS3A1083
                  10.  Ms. Kavya Priya.L - 20LS3A1084






                                             2021 Batch





                  1. Ms. Anumita Mazumdar - 21FRSA11

                  2. Ms. Nishani Sahoo - 21FRSA37

                  3. Ms. Siddhi Pant - 21FRSA53

                  4. Ms. Merien Abraham - 21FRSB49


























                                                          146]]></page><page Index="148"><![CDATA[]]></page></pages></Search>